<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">Threat of Conversion in the Earliest Syriac Writings on Islam?</title><title>Studies on the Children of Abraham 8</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/24VWXDLL/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><analytic><author><forename>Serafim</forename><surname>Seppälä</surname></author><title level="a">Threat of Conversion in the Earliest Syriac Writings on Islam?</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/24VWXDLL</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/24VWXDLL</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/24VWXDLL</idno></analytic><monogr><editor><forename>Timo</forename><surname>Nisula</surname></editor><editor><forename>Anni Maria</forename><surname>Laato</surname></editor><editor><forename>Pablo</forename><surname>Irizar</surname></editor><title level="m">Religious Polemics and Encounters in Late Antiquity: Boundaries, Conversions, and Persuasion</title><imprint><pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace><publisher>Brill</publisher><date>2021</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">258-284</biblScope></monogr><series><title>Studies on the Children of Abraham 8</title></series><note type="abstract">Christian sources of mid seventh
                    century give relatively little attention to Muslims and even less to Islam, but
                    the number of references is still considerable. The Christian approach to early
                    Islam and Muslim rule was mostly negative, or at best neutral, but in the early
                    sources this was not because of the contents of Islamic belief but because of
                    what the Islamic rule did to Christians. Insiders’ and outsiders’ perspectives
                    on Islam and Muslims were constantly at odds, however, and should not be
                    confused. When the Muslim rule was established and the society started to adapt
                    the Islamic system, conversions started to take place on growing numbers. The
                    first known cases are rather early and imply that a noteworthy number of
                    conversions took place even in the pre-Umayyad era in some places. The
                    dominating motive seems to have been the will to avoid the discriminating
                    taxation. Had there been a considerable amount of conversions because of the
                    belief in the Quranic revelation, theological authors would certainly have
                    reacted heavily. It was only in Abbasid times, however, that a need for
                    theological apologies appeared. Even if the early cases of conversion were
                    somewhat random, they were nevertheless unprecedented. Apart from certain cases
                    during the persecutions of the early Church, conversions away from Christianity
                    in the Christian East had been almost non-existent. Therefore, the Islamic rule
                    was perceived and interpreted as an apocalyptic disaster: Rome or Persia had not
                    been able to conquer the Church by persecution, but for the first time in
                    history, big numbers of Christians were denouncing their faith. This process
                    intensified in latter half of the eighth century, but it was already on the rise
                    a century earlier.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Seppälä, Serafim. “Threat of Conversion in the Earliest Syriac Writings on Islam?” In <title level="m">Religious Polemics and Encounters in Late Antiquity: Boundaries, Conversions, and Persuasion</title>, edited by Timo Nisula, Anni Maria Laato, and Pablo Irizar, 258–84. Studies on the Children of Abraham 8. Leiden: Brill, 2021.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Abook&amp;amp;rft.genre=bookitem&amp;amp;rft.atitle=Threat%20of%20Conversion%20in%20the%20Earliest%20Syriac%20Writings%20on%20Islam%3F&amp;amp;rft.btitle=Religious%20Polemics%20and%20Encounters%20in%20Late%20Antiquity%3A%20Boundaries%2C%20Conversions%2C%20and%20Persuasion&amp;amp;rft.place=Leiden&amp;amp;rft.publisher=Brill&amp;amp;rft.series=Studies%20on%20the%20Children%20of%20Abraham%208&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Serafim&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Sepp%C3%A4l%C3%A4&amp;amp;rft.au=Serafim%20Sepp%C3%A4l%C3%A4&amp;amp;rft.au=Timo%20Nisula&amp;amp;rft.au=Anni%20Maria%20Laato&amp;amp;rft.au=Pablo%20Irizar&amp;amp;rft.date=2021&amp;amp;rft.pages=258-284&amp;amp;rft.spage=258&amp;amp;rft.epage=284"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Serafim Seppälä, <title level="a">Threat of Conversion in the Earliest Syriac Writings on Islam?,</title> in <title level="m">Religious Polemics and Encounters in Late Antiquity: Boundaries, Conversions, and Persuasion</title>, ed. Timo Nisula, Anni Maria Laato, and Pablo Irizar, Studies on the Children of Abraham 8 (Leiden: Brill, 2021), 258–84.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>