<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Sectarian Scripture: The Qur’ān’s Dogmatic Re-articulation of the Aramaic Gospel Traditions in the Late Antique Near East</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/2RGXGA69/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Emran</forename><surname>El-Badawi</surname></author><title level="m">Sectarian Scripture: The Qur’ān’s Dogmatic Re-articulation of the Aramaic Gospel Traditions in the Late Antique Near East</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/2RGXGA69</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/2RGXGA69</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/2RGXGA69</idno><imprint><date>2011</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">As a scripture of the late antique Near East (180-632 CE), the Qur'an was in dialogue with numerous impulses coming from the Judeo-Christian as well as Zoroastrian sphere. The religious movement within which the Qur'an arose was the religion preached by Muh[dotbelow]ammad (d. 632), whose Arabic name Islam paralleled that of the waning mashlman uta , or "prophetic tradition," of the Syriac speaking churches, and which patriarchs like John of Ephesus (d. 586) and Babai the Great (d. 628) sought to reconsolidate.
The Qur'an identifies the two scriptures with which it is in greatest dialogue as al-tawrah (Q 5:44), or Hebrew Scripture and Rabbinic commentary, and al-inj il (Q 5:47), or the Gospels. The latter, which left an indelible mark on the Qur'an's language and worldview, is dubbed here the "Aramaic Gospel Traditions." Specifically, these are the extant Gospel recensions preserved in the Syriac and Christian Palestinian Aramaic dialects. Based on Muhammad's vision of strict monotheism the Qur'an challenged or adopted the language and imagery of the Aramaic Gospel Traditions through a process called "dogmatic re-articulation."
This study demonstrates the process of dogmatic re-articulation by undertaking a comparative, literary analysis of qur'anic verses and corresponding verses from the Aramaic Gospels. There are four general themes under which this literary analysis takes place: the prophets and their righteous entourage; the evils of the clergy; the divine realm; and finally divine judgment and the apocalypse. This study contributes to recent literature on Qur'anic Studies and Islamic Origins by Gabriel Reynolds, Fred Donner, Sidney Griffith, Angelika Neuwirth, and Nasr H. Abu Zayd.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  El-Badawi, Emran. “Sectarian Scripture: The Qur’ān’s Dogmatic Re-Articulation of the Aramaic Gospel Traditions in the Late Antique Near East.” Ph.D. dissertation, University of Chicago, 2011.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Sectarian%20Scripture%3A%20The%20Qur%E2%80%99%C4%81n%E2%80%99s%20Dogmatic%20Re-articulation%20of%20the%20Aramaic%20Gospel%20Traditions%20in%20the%20Late%20Antique%20Near%20East&amp;amp;rft.inst=University%20of%20Chicago&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Emran&amp;amp;rft.aulast=El-Badawi&amp;amp;rft.au=Emran%20El-Badawi&amp;amp;rft.date=2011"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Emran El-Badawi, <title level="a">Sectarian Scripture: The Qur’ān’s Dogmatic Re-Articulation of the Aramaic Gospel Traditions in the Late Antique Near East</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, University of Chicago, 2011).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>