<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The Hymns of David Interpreted in Syriac: A Study of Translation Technique in the First Book of the Book of Psalms (Ps 1-41) in the Pešitta</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/2ULZYFK2/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-06-18-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-06-18-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="thesis"><monogr><author><forename>Jan-Erik</forename><surname>Eriksson</surname></author><title level="m">The Hymns of David Interpreted in Syriac: A Study of Translation Technique in the First Book of the Book of Psalms (Ps 1-41) in the Pešitta</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/2ULZYFK2</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/2ULZYFK2</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/2ULZYFK2</idno><imprint><date>1989</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">As far as the Old Testament is concerned, the study of the translation technique of ancient Biblical translations has generally dealt with the Greek translation, the Septuagint. Often a representative detail of the text has been chosen to give evidence for conclusions about the translation technique as a whole. A quite different method of analysis has been suggested by Prof. James Barr. The method aims in principle to analyse every detail of the translation. This should be done on four levels: (a) word order; (b) quantitative differences (additions and substractions); (c) consistency; (d) accuracy. Only differences between the original and the translation should be noted and labelled 'free'. Within each level the translation, according to a percentage notation, could then be placed in a scale literal-free. No average judgement of a translation could be made from this method of analysis. Using the method described, the translation technique of the First Book of the Book of Psalms (Ps 1-41) in the Pesitta has been analysed.
Part I. Introduction. The examination scheme of Prof. Barr has been discussed and modified for Syriac conditions.
Part II. Investigation. This part follows a detailed examination, according to the modified examination scheme, of the translation verse by verse.
Part III. Conclusions. The occurrences of free translations, according to the examination scheme, are ordered systematically point by point in the scheme. Particularly in the points dealing with accuracy in the scheme, the free translations are further analysed and arranged systematically. Every point in the examination scheme emerges in a percentage notation of free translations. The feature consistency has not been satisfyingly examined. The question of the Vorlage has been essential in the analysis. It has been maintained that the translator has made his translation from a Hebrew text under influence from the Greek Septuagint. The Hebrew Vorlage did not differ much from the consonants of the Massoretic text, but the translation indicates several differences in pronunciation and division of the text. The sudden and unexpected nature of the Greek influence is explained by the fact that the translator probably had the Greek text stored in his memory rather than in front of him.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Eriksson, Jan-Erik. “The Hymns of David Interpreted in Syriac: A Study of Translation Technique in the First Book of the Book of Psalms (Ps 1-41) in the Pešitta.” Th.D. dissertation, University of Uppsala, 1989.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=The%20Hymns%20of%20David%20Interpreted%20in%20Syriac%3A%20A%20Study%20of%20Translation%20Technique%20in%20the%20First%20Book%20of%20the%20Book%20of%20Psalms%20(Ps%201-41)%20in%20the%20Pe%C5%A1itta&amp;amp;rft.inst=University%20of%20Uppsala&amp;amp;rft.degree=Th.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Jan-Erik&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Eriksson&amp;amp;rft.au=Jan-Erik%20Eriksson&amp;amp;rft.date=1989&amp;amp;rft.tpages=207"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Jan-Erik Eriksson, <title level="a">The Hymns of David Interpreted in Syriac: A Study of Translation Technique in the First Book of the Book of Psalms (Ps 1-41) in the Pešitta</title> (Th.D. dissertation, University of Uppsala, 1989).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/2ULZYFK2" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Old Testament</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/2ULZYFK2" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Peshitta OT</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/2ULZYFK2" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Psalms</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/2ULZYFK2" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>translation</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>