<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Théodoret de Cyr, &lt;i&gt;Interpretatio in Epistulam ad Romanos&lt;/i&gt;: édition, traduction et commentaire</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/3QCYYSVF/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2025-05-20-05:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2025-05-20-05:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Agnès</forename><surname>Lorrain</surname></author><title level="m">Théodoret de Cyr, &lt;i&gt;Interpretatio in Epistulam ad Romanos&lt;/i&gt;: édition, traduction et commentaire</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/3QCYYSVF</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/3QCYYSVF</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/3QCYYSVF</idno><imprint><date>2015</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">Theodoret of Cyrrhus’s &lt;i&gt;In epistulas Pauli&lt;/i&gt; (5th c.) is the oldest surviving Greek commentary that has been preserved in the original language. This dissertation presents a critical edition of Theodoret’s prologue and commentary on the Epistle to the Romans based on all the extant direct manuscripts as well as one catena manuscript. It also offers the first translation of the work into the French language. While many scholars have studied the principles and methods of Antiochene exegesis for the Old Testament, the methods used for the New Testament remain largely unexamined. Through different thematic studies, the dissertation explores the exegetical approach which deals with and is shaped by this latter corpus specifically. By analyzing the elements that structure its discourse as well as its semantic tendencies, it sets out to reveal the central features of Theodoret’s exegetical approach despite the minimal distance which he maintains between the Biblical text and his commentary. Special attention is also paid to Theodoret’s use of the works of John Chrysostom in his own writing. Finally, the dissertation explores the relationship between Theodoret’s biblical exegesis and the rich tradition of scriptural quotation both in a historical and theological context. The main focus is on his polemical discourses on the Jews and the Marcionites and also in his writings on the Trinitarian and Christological controversies. Through a careful analysis of the exegete’s approach to scriptural argumentation and his use of sources, we hope to reveal the richness and versatility of a work which, at first glance, appears to be little more than a simple paraphrase of the biblical text.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Lorrain, Agnès. “Théodoret de Cyr, <title level="m">Interpretatio in Epistulam Ad Romanos</title>: Édition, Traduction et Commentaire.” Thèse de doctorat, Université Paris-Sorbonne ‒ Paris IV, 2015.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Th%C3%A9odoret%20de%20Cyr%2C%20%3Ci%3EInterpretatio%20in%20Epistulam%20ad%20Romanos%3C%2Fi%3E%3A%20%C3%A9dition%2C%20traduction%20et%20commentaire&amp;amp;rft.inst=Universit%C3%A9%20Paris-Sorbonne%20%E2%80%92%20Paris%20IV&amp;amp;rft.degree=Th%C3%A8se%20de%20doctorat&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Agn%C3%A8s&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Lorrain&amp;amp;rft.au=Agn%C3%A8s%20Lorrain&amp;amp;rft.date=2015"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Agnès Lorrain, <title level="a">Théodoret de Cyr, Interpretatio in Epistulam Ad Romanos</title>: Édition, Traduction et Commentaire” (Thèse de doctorat, Université Paris-Sorbonne ‒ Paris IV, 2015).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>