<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Le morphème d= en araméen-syriaque: étude d’une polyfonctionalité à plusieurs échelles syntaxiques</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/47IQW9AH/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-06-17-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-06-17-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="thesis"><monogr><author><forename>Roula</forename><surname>Skaf</surname></author><title level="m">Le morphème d= en araméen-syriaque: étude d’une polyfonctionalité à plusieurs échelles syntaxiques</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/47IQW9AH</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/47IQW9AH</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/47IQW9AH</idno><imprint><date>2015</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The behaviour of the polyfunctional morpheme d= in the Syriac language of the Gospels of the Peshiṭta is described in a typological perspective, in synchrony and in comparison, for some properties, with other varieties of Syriac and with other Semitic languages. d=, a former demonstrative in Proto-Semitic, is a relator at various syntactic levels: a determination place-holder, a genitival and relative marker, an introducer of completive and adverbial clauses.Chapter 1 introduces the topic of the study and the theoretical framework and chapter 2 discusses the state of art.Chapter 3 is dedicated to the study of the genitive phrase. We discovered that a syntactic criterion allows to distinguish semantically between alienable and inalienable phrases, to different degrees according to the semantic categories of the inalienable set, i.e. kinship and body part terms.In chapter 4, we showed that even though syntactic structures are similar for restrictive and non-restrictive relative clauses, it is impossible to relativize the latter for object, dative and adjoint relatives clauses. The syntactic gap strategy constitutes the primary strategy in the accessibility hierarchy and all the functions of the head in the main clause, except the object of comparison, are relativizable.Chapter 5 deals with the functions of d= as a complementizer and an introducer of adverbial clauses. The complementizer uses are wider than in Old Semitic. d= is employed with 12 of the 14 types of predicates of Noonan's typological classification as against 3 in Old Semitic. Syriac conforms to the implicational hierarchy named Complement Deranking-Argument Hierarchy. For adverbial clauses, the syntactic criterion of saturation of the verbal valency as well as semantic and contextual criteria permit to distinguish adverbial clauses from complement clauses. When d= forms conjunctive locutions with prepositions or adverbs, the polysemy of values is disambiguated thanks to the context. Only the conjunction mo d= is monosemous (with a temporal meaning).In the last chapter (chap. 6) on reported speech, we showed that direct reported speech is mostly introduced without d=, whereas it is always the case for indirect speech. Greek did not have any influence on the use of d=.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Skaf, Roula. “Le Morphème D= En Araméen-Syriaque: Étude d’une Polyfonctionalité à Plusieurs Échelles Syntaxiques.” Thèse de doctorat, Université Sorbonne Paris Cité, 2015.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Le%20morph%C3%A8me%20d%3D%20en%20aram%C3%A9en-syriaque%3A%20%C3%A9tude%20d%E2%80%99une%20polyfonctionalit%C3%A9%20%C3%A0%20plusieurs%20%C3%A9chelles%20syntaxiques&amp;amp;rft.inst=Universit%C3%A9%20Sorbonne%20Paris%20Cit%C3%A9&amp;amp;rft.degree=Th%C3%A8se%20de%20doctorat&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Roula&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Skaf&amp;amp;rft.au=Roula%20Skaf&amp;amp;rft.date=2015"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Roula Skaf, <title level="a">Le Morphème D= En Araméen-Syriaque: Étude d’une Polyfonctionalité à Plusieurs Échelles Syntaxiques</title> (Thèse de doctorat, Université Sorbonne Paris Cité, 2015).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/47IQW9AH" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Classical Syriac</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/47IQW9AH" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Syriac language</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/47IQW9AH" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>grammar</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/47IQW9AH" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>syntax</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>