<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">The Maronite College in Early Modern Rome: Between the Ottoman Empire and the Republic of Letters</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/4N38KIJT/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2025-05-20-05:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2025-05-20-05:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="bookSection"><analytic><author><forename>Aurélien</forename><surname>Girard</surname></author><author><forename>Giovanni</forename><surname>Pizzorusso</surname></author><title level="a">The Maronite College in Early Modern Rome: Between the Ottoman Empire and the Republic of Letters</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/4N38KIJT</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/4N38KIJT</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/4N38KIJT</idno></analytic><monogr><editor><forename>Liam</forename><surname>Chambers</surname></editor><editor><forename>Thomas</forename><surname>O’Connor</surname></editor><title level="m">College Communities Abroad: Education, Migration and Catholicism in Early Modern Europe</title><imprint><pubPlace>Manchester</pubPlace><publisher>Manchester University Press</publisher><date>2017</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">174-197</biblScope></monogr><note type="abstract">In the early modern period, Catholic communities under Protestant jurisdictions were not alone in establishing collegial networks in Catholic centres. The Maronites, a Christian Church in communion with Rome faced educational challenges similar to those of Catholic communities in western Protestant states. A Maronite College was founded in Rome in 1584, on the model of others Catholic colleges created in Rome in the second part of the sixteenth century. Until now, traditional Maronite and Lebanese historiography has tended to treat the institution in isolation from the other collegial networks and from the global perspective of the papacy on the challenge of educating national clergies in non-Catholic jurisdictions. This essay presents an overview of the Maronite College in Rome, outlining the context for its foundation (the Roman Catholic mission in the Near East) and the links with others colleges. To plot the evolution of the institution, two versions of the college rules (1585 and 1732) are compared. They were influenced by the changing attitudes of the papacy, the foundation of Propaganda Fide, the activities of the Jesuits and changes within the Maronite patriarchate itself. The second part establishes a profile of the early modern staff and students of the college. Details are available on 280 Maronite students received by the institution between 1584 and 1788. For the young Maronites, life in Rome was difficult, with changes in diet and conditions, financial worries and cultural challenges. There were frequent interventions by the Lebanese authorities with the Jesuit college managers. Special attention is paid to the course of studies in Rome and academic links with other Roman institutions, especially neighbouring Jesuit colleges. The third part discusses the links between the Roman college and changes in the middle-eastern Maronite community. The Maronite college was the main European gateway for the Maronites. Some eastern Catholics chose to remain in Europe, often to follow academic careers. Attention is also paid to the relationship between the College and the Maronite diaspora and its links with intellectual life in the West. In the latter context, the role of the College library and its manuscript collection in facilitating Western academic access to oriental languages and thought is described. Like other networks, the Maronite college fulfilled a broad range of functions that went well beyond the simple training of clergy.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Girard, Aurélien, and Giovanni Pizzorusso. “The Maronite College in Early Modern Rome: Between the Ottoman Empire and the Republic of Letters.” In <title level="m">College Communities Abroad: Education, Migration and Catholicism in Early Modern Europe</title>, edited by Liam Chambers and Thomas O’Connor, 174–97. Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2017.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Abook&amp;amp;rft.genre=bookitem&amp;amp;rft.atitle=The%20Maronite%20College%20in%20Early%20Modern%20Rome%3A%20Between%20the%20Ottoman%20Empire%20and%20the%20Republic%20of%20Letters&amp;amp;rft.btitle=College%20Communities%20Abroad%3A%20Education%2C%20Migration%20and%20Catholicism%20in%20Early%20Modern%20Europe&amp;amp;rft.place=Manchester&amp;amp;rft.publisher=Manchester%20University%20Press&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Aur%C3%A9lien&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Girard&amp;amp;rft.au=Aur%C3%A9lien%20Girard&amp;amp;rft.au=Giovanni%20Pizzorusso&amp;amp;rft.au=Liam%20Chambers&amp;amp;rft.au=Thomas%20O%E2%80%99Connor&amp;amp;rft.date=2017&amp;amp;rft.pages=174-197&amp;amp;rft.spage=174&amp;amp;rft.epage=197"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Aurélien Girard and Giovanni Pizzorusso, <title level="a">The Maronite College in Early Modern Rome: Between the Ottoman Empire and the Republic of Letters,</title> in <title level="m">College Communities Abroad: Education, Migration and Catholicism in Early Modern Europe</title>, ed. Liam Chambers and Thomas O’Connor (Manchester: Manchester University Press, 2017), 174–97.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>