<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Pilgerstätten in der syrischen Peripherie: Eine ethnologische Studie zur kognitiven Konstruktion sakraler Plätze und deren Praxisrelevanz</title><title level="s">Sitzungsberichte der Österreichische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Philosophisch-Historische Klasse 700 = Veröffentlichungen zur Sozialanthropologie 5</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/5IKJDZSN/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Gebhard</forename><surname>Fartacek</surname></author><title level="m">Pilgerstätten in der syrischen Peripherie: Eine ethnologische Studie zur kognitiven Konstruktion sakraler Plätze und deren Praxisrelevanz</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/5IKJDZSN</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/5IKJDZSN</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/5IKJDZSN</idno><imprint><pubPlace>Wien</pubPlace><publisher>Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften</publisher><date>2003</date></imprint></monogr><series><title level="s">Sitzungsberichte der Österreichische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Philosophisch-Historische Klasse 700 = Veröffentlichungen zur Sozialanthropologie 5</title></series><note type="abstract">The Holy Land and Syria have attracted pilgrims since biblical times. Many of the twenty pilgrimage centres in remote areas of the Druse country and south east of Damascus which the author describes are connected with the lives of Old Testament heroes, as well as Christian and Moslem saints. The author's well-illustrated book is founded largely on his interviews with those connected with the shrines he visited. Though the predominant influence is Sunni Moslem, some important Christian centres remain, such as the supposed burial place of St George revered in the Greek Orthodox church at Azra in the Druze country. Legends of Christian martyrs, such as the Seven Dormants, are also commemorated in purely Moslem settings. The pilgrimage centres, often originally Grottoes, form a point of unity between ordinarily rival faiths in Syria. Christians and Moslems visit the shrines for the same purpose, namely to obtain something of the sacred influence (&lt;i&gt;baraka&lt;/i&gt;) of the saint whose memory is preserved. The increase in the popularity of these shrines, in contrast to what this reviewer has witnessed in Tunisia, is interesting, as is their long continued veneration. The study would have been improved by some comparison with the centres visited by the pilgrim Egeria in the fourth century. Evidence for continuity would have been a valuable contribution to the religious history of Syria and Palestine. As it is, the author has provided a well-researched foundation for the study of an aspect of the relations between Christianity and Islam in Syria. [W.H.C. Frend]</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Fartacek, Gebhard. <title level="m">Pilgerstätten in Der Syrischen Peripherie: Eine Ethnologische Studie Zur Kognitiven Konstruktion Sakraler Plätze Und Deren Praxisrelevanz</title>. Sitzungsberichte Der Österreichische Akademie Der Wissenschaften, Philosophisch-Historische Klasse 700 = Veröffentlichungen Zur Sozialanthropologie 5. Wien: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2003.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Abook&amp;amp;rft.genre=book&amp;amp;rft.btitle=Pilgerst%C3%A4tten%20in%20der%20syrischen%20Peripherie%3A%20Eine%20ethnologische%20Studie%20zur%20kognitiven%20Konstruktion%20sakraler%20Pl%C3%A4tze%20und%20deren%20Praxisrelevanz&amp;amp;rft.place=Wien&amp;amp;rft.publisher=Verlag%20der%20%C3%96sterreichischen%20Akademie%20der%20Wissenschaften&amp;amp;rft.series=Sitzungsberichte%20der%20%C3%96sterreichische%20Akademie%20der%20Wissenschaften%2C%20Philosophisch-Historische%20Klasse%20700%20%3D%20Ver%C3%B6ffentlichungen%20zur%20Sozialanthropologie%205&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Gebhard&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Fartacek&amp;amp;rft.au=Gebhard%20Fartacek&amp;amp;rft.date=2003&amp;amp;rft.tpages=223"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Gebhard Fartacek, <title level="m">Pilgerstätten in Der Syrischen Peripherie: Eine Ethnologische Studie Zur Kognitiven Konstruktion Sakraler Plätze Und Deren Praxisrelevanz</title>, Sitzungsberichte Der Österreichische Akademie Der Wissenschaften, Philosophisch-Historische Klasse 700 = Veröffentlichungen Zur Sozialanthropologie 5 (Wien: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2003).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>