<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">Reflection of Mongolian Imperial Ideas in the Medieval Syrian Sources</title><title level="j">Восток / Oriens</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/5K2KK2ZP/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><analytic><author><forename>Yuliy I.</forename><surname>Drobyshev</surname></author><title level="a">Reflection of Mongolian Imperial Ideas in the Medieval Syrian Sources</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/5K2KK2ZP</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/5K2KK2ZP</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/5K2KK2ZP</idno></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Восток / Oriens</title><textLang mainLang="Russian"/><biblScope unit="vol">1</biblScope><imprint><date>2021</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">19-30</biblScope></monogr><note type="abstract">The article continues the theme of reflection of the Mongol imperial ideology in medieval sources of countries and regions faced with the Mongol invasion in the 13th century [Drobyshev, 2019, Drobyshev, 2020]. The peculiarities of mentality, cultural traditions, including those related to annals, the nature of the Mongol invasion and formation of the Mongol power in occupied lands determined the differences in the perception of this new formidable political force. Syrian historiography during the Mongol rule was firmly adhered to the tradition laid down by the Roman historian Eusebius of Caesarea (CA. 265–339/340) in his famous “Ecclesiastical history”. In view of the absence of a secular Syriac-speaking upper class, it was exclusively religious, addressed to educated priests and monks, therefore, all events were considered by its authors as the unfolding of the plan for the salvation of mankind by God. Based on this premise, the Syrian authors chose the facts of political or military history, placing in place every person who acted according to the will of Divine Providence, including, of course, the Mongols – from the great khans to ordinary soldiers. This peculiarity of Syrian historiography opens a new frontier in our understanding of the Mongols’ aggressive plans, the claims of their khans to universal rule, and the methods of justifying these claims for the conquered peoples. The author focuses on the anonymous “History of Mar Yahballaha III and Rabban Sauma” and “The General History” by Abu’l-Faraj, and also draws on a number of other, less widely known sources. It is shown that in line with the Syrian historiography, which obviously continues an ancient regional tradition, there are differences in denomination of the Mongol rulers (khan/khagan), and the universality of the local Mongol power is exaggerated, however, there is no information about the Mongols’ plans to conquer “the whole world”. Indeed, the focus of Syrian historians is on rulers of the Ilkhanate, who determined policy in the Middle East in those years and had a significant influence on religious climate of the region, often favoring Christians.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Drobyshev, Yuliy I. “Reflection of Mongolian Imperial Ideas in the Medieval Syrian Sources.” <title level="m">Восток / Oriens</title> 1 (2021): 19–30. https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.31857/S086919080013354-6.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_id=info%3Adoi%2Fhttps%3A%2F%2Fdoi.org%2F10.31857%2FS086919080013354-6&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Ajournal&amp;amp;rft.genre=article&amp;amp;rft.atitle=Reflection%20of%20Mongolian%20Imperial%20Ideas%20in%20the%20Medieval%20Syrian%20Sources&amp;amp;rft.jtitle=%D0%92%D0%BE%D1%81%D1%82%D0%BE%D0%BA%20%2F%20Oriens&amp;amp;rft.volume=1&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Yuliy%20I.&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Drobyshev&amp;amp;rft.au=Yuliy%20I.%20Drobyshev&amp;amp;rft.date=2021&amp;amp;rft.pages=19-30&amp;amp;rft.spage=19&amp;amp;rft.epage=30&amp;amp;rft.language=Russian"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Yuliy I. Drobyshev, <title level="a">Reflection of Mongolian Imperial Ideas in the Medieval Syrian Sources,</title> <title level="m">Восток / Oriens</title> 1 (2021): 19–30, https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.31857/S086919080013354-6.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>