<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">A Comparative Lexicon of Three Modern Aramaic Dialects (Middle East, United States)</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/5YF3UUJ4/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Florence Gertrude</forename><surname>Kuipers</surname></author><title level="m">A Comparative Lexicon of Three Modern Aramaic Dialects (Middle East, United States)</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/5YF3UUJ4</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/5YF3UUJ4</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/5YF3UUJ4</idno><imprint><date>1983</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">This study provides a basic lexicon or dictionary for each of three Modern Aramaic dialects which are currently well represented in the United States and renders the vocabulary comparative by relating it to a single listing in the source language (English). The three dialects of interest are: (1) Telkeppe Chaldean with 30,000 speakers in Detroit, Michigan and smaller groups of speakers elsewhere, (2) Assyrian with speakers principally in Chicago, Ill. and California, and (3) Turoyo (Syrian) with speakers principally in New Jersey and other areas of the Northeast. The lexicon has a total of 2,110 English entries for all form classes exclusive of the verb and 377 English entries for the verb. The dialect entries, which are frequently multiple, are words elicited from selected native speakers in the United States. They are in a phonemic transcription based on tape recordings. The lexicon also has an introduction, providing background information on the dialects of interest as well as a full explanation of the lexicon.
For the present and future purposes of the lexicon the compiler saw a distinct advantage in not combining these dialects into a single composite listing, but in maintaining a separate listing for each. In the homelands of the Aramaic-speaking people (primarily Turkey, Iran, Iraq, and Syria) every district or town has its own dialect, and frequently, depending upon geographical proximity, these dialects differ from each other considerably, both phonologically and lexically. For example, in the case of the three above-mentioned ones, Turoyo, spoken in Turkey, is western Aramaic and is mutually unintelligible with Telkeppe Chaldean and Assyrian, which are eastern Aramaic. This lexicon should prove helpful to scholars and language learners as a working aid or as a dictionary for any one of the dialects represented, but also should be valuable source material for a more comprehensive comparative study of Modern Aramaic.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Kuipers, Florence Gertrude. “A Comparative Lexicon of Three Modern Aramaic Dialects (Middle East, United States).” Ph.D. dissertation, Georgetown University, 1983.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=A%20Comparative%20Lexicon%20of%20Three%20Modern%20Aramaic%20Dialects%20(Middle%20East%2C%20United%20States)&amp;amp;rft.inst=Georgetown%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Florence%20Gertrude&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Kuipers&amp;amp;rft.au=Florence%20Gertrude%20Kuipers&amp;amp;rft.date=1983"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Florence Gertrude Kuipers, <title level="a">A Comparative Lexicon of Three Modern Aramaic Dialects (Middle East, United States)</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, Georgetown University, 1983).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>