<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Byzantine Northern Syria, A.D. 298-610: Integration and Disintegration</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/6QNAQETV/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Dennis Dean</forename><surname>Hammond</surname></author><title level="m">Byzantine Northern Syria, A.D. 298-610: Integration and Disintegration</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/6QNAQETV</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/6QNAQETV</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/6QNAQETV</idno><imprint><date>1987</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">Byzantine Northern Syria, despite its great cultural and ethnic complexity, in the fourth century entered a period when certain Syrian groups became integrated with the Byzantine state. This was helped by the economic decline of the traditional local establishment including the decurions and the temple complexes. It was further encouraged by the growing presence of the state apparatus in local Syrian affairs. Finally, it was the Christian ecclesiastical organization which tended to replace many of the elements of traditional civic government and, in time, become the only local entity capable of working with the state in carrying out policy and in the maintenance of Byzantine rule.
In the evolving relationship of bishop and state, two important factors were the traditional high-priest, the archiereus, and the provincial assemblies. The failed attempts of Maximinus Daia and Julian to create a state religion centered on the office of provincial archierosyne, influenced the way the state was to develop its official relationship with the Christian bishops. Out of this came the strong political role of bishops, especially those who held the episcopal thrones of provincial capitals. These bishops and their local ecclesiastical organizations were the Syrian groups that became integrated with the Byzantine state. To the state they brought many of the popular religious practices of Syrian Christians including the honoring of monks; the belief in the efficacy of relics; the growing worship of icons; and the interest in the lives of the martyrs and anchorites as heroes of the Church, to mention only a few.
This integration of certain segments of Syrian society was countered by certain disintegrating tendencies which existed in northern Syria among which were the various religious factions and the proximity of the Persian Empire.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Hammond, Dennis Dean. “Byzantine Northern Syria, A.D. 298-610: Integration and Disintegration.” Ph.D. dissertation, University of California, Los Angeles, 1987.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Byzantine%20Northern%20Syria%2C%20A.D.%20298-610%3A%20Integration%20and%20Disintegration&amp;amp;rft.inst=University%20of%20California%2C%20Los%20Angeles&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Dennis%20Dean&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Hammond&amp;amp;rft.au=Dennis%20Dean%20Hammond&amp;amp;rft.date=1987"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Dennis Dean Hammond, <title level="a">Byzantine Northern Syria, A.D. 298-610: Integration and Disintegration</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, University of California, Los Angeles, 1987).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>