<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">L’Esposizione XIV di Afraate: una retorica antiautoritaria nel contesto dell’evoluzione istituzionale della Chiesa siriaca</title><title>Orientalia Ambrosiana 3</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/8ST667RT/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><analytic><author><forename>Alberto</forename><surname>Camplani</surname></author><title level="a">L’Esposizione XIV di Afraate: una retorica antiautoritaria nel contesto dell’evoluzione istituzionale della Chiesa siriaca</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/8ST667RT</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/8ST667RT</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/8ST667RT</idno></analytic><monogr><editor><forename>Carmela</forename><surname>Baffioni</surname></editor><editor><forename>Rosa Bianca</forename><surname>Finazzi</surname></editor><editor><forename>Anna</forename><surname>Passoni Dell’Acqua</surname></editor><editor><forename>Emidio</forename><surname>Vergani</surname></editor><title level="m">Storia e pensiero religioso nel Vicino Oriente: l’età Bagratide – Maimonide – Afraate</title><imprint><pubPlace>Milano</pubPlace><publisher>Biblioteca Ambrosiana / Roma: Bulzoni</publisher><date>2014</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">191-235</biblScope></monogr><series><title>Orientalia Ambrosiana 3</title></series><note type="abstract">The aim of this paper is to place the XIV Exposition by Aphrahat in the crisis caused in Persia by the progressive institutionalization of the church hierarchy, in particular in the authoritarian evolution of the monarchical episcopate and the formation of metropolitan structures in an area that has experienced the most archaic forms of organization of the Christian communities. While the most recent scholarship has interpreted this letter on the backdrop of the anti-Christian persecution that began in the Sassanid Empire in 341, which led the primate of Seleucia-Ctesiphon to negotiate between Christian communities and the state, here the proposal is made to understand the most famous expressions by Aphraates in reference not to the behaviour of the bishop of Seleucia, but to the structure of the church, and as a severe criticism of the figure of the bishop and metropolitan which is emerging in the context of the Persian church. This polemical attitude in not intended as a defense of a charismatic leadership of the Church, or as a propotion of the urban ascetics known as “bnay qyāmā “, but seems to be rxpressed in view of an old ideal of the Christian leader , able to moderate his power, to accept differences of ideology , to exercise judgment and forgiveness , to exert his episcopal ministry in collaboration with his peers and the presbytery, according to a conservative model of Church leadership in decline in the fourth century. This reading of the Exposition XIV is based on a close comparison of the most important statements by Aphrahat with both the Didascalia Apostolorum, a true manifesto of the monarchical episcopate, and the synodical letter written about Paul of Samosata by the bishops gathered in the council fo Antioch of 268, partially preserved by Eusebius of Caesarea (h.e., VII , 30, 2-17)</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Camplani, Alberto. “L’Esposizione XIV Di Afraate: Una Retorica Antiautoritaria Nel Contesto Dell’evoluzione Istituzionale Della Chiesa Siriaca.” In <title level="m">Storia e Pensiero Religioso Nel Vicino Oriente: L’età Bagratide – Maimonide – Afraate</title>, edited by Carmela Baffioni, Rosa Bianca Finazzi, Anna Passoni Dell’Acqua, and Emidio Vergani, 191–235. Orientalia Ambrosiana 3. Milano: Biblioteca Ambrosiana / Roma: Bulzoni, 2014.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Abook&amp;amp;rft.genre=bookitem&amp;amp;rft.atitle=L%E2%80%99Esposizione%20XIV%20di%20Afraate%3A%20una%20retorica%20antiautoritaria%20nel%20contesto%20dell%E2%80%99evoluzione%20istituzionale%20della%20Chiesa%20siriaca&amp;amp;rft.btitle=Storia%20e%20pensiero%20religioso%20nel%20Vicino%20Oriente%3A%20l%E2%80%99et%C3%A0%20Bagratide%20%E2%80%93%20Maimonide%20%E2%80%93%20Afraate&amp;amp;rft.place=Milano&amp;amp;rft.publisher=Biblioteca%20Ambrosiana%20%2F%20Roma%3A%20Bulzoni&amp;amp;rft.series=Orientalia%20Ambrosiana%203&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Alberto&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Camplani&amp;amp;rft.au=Alberto%20Camplani&amp;amp;rft.au=Carmela%20Baffioni&amp;amp;rft.au=Rosa%20Bianca%20Finazzi&amp;amp;rft.au=Anna%20Passoni%20Dell%E2%80%99Acqua&amp;amp;rft.au=Emidio%20Vergani&amp;amp;rft.date=2014&amp;amp;rft.pages=191-235&amp;amp;rft.spage=191&amp;amp;rft.epage=235"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Alberto Camplani, <title level="a">L’Esposizione XIV Di Afraate: Una Retorica Antiautoritaria Nel Contesto Dell’evoluzione Istituzionale Della Chiesa Siriaca,</title> in <title level="m">Storia e Pensiero Religioso Nel Vicino Oriente: L’età Bagratide – Maimonide – Afraate</title>, ed. Carmela Baffioni et al., Orientalia Ambrosiana 3 (Milano: Biblioteca Ambrosiana / Roma: Bulzoni, 2014), 191–235.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>