<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Objective Pronominal Suffixes in Aramaic</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/98EEI6QF/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Stephan Frank</forename><surname>Bennett</surname></author><title level="m">Objective Pronominal Suffixes in Aramaic</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/98EEI6QF</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/98EEI6QF</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/98EEI6QF</idno><imprint><date>1984</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">This work is a discussion of the development of the objective pronominal suffixes used on the perfect, imperfect and imperative verbal forms in Aramaic. It covers the time period from the earliest attestations of Aramaic through the Late Aramaic dialects. The chapters are arranged chronologically starting with Old Aramaic and present the evidence from each period followed by a discussion of that evidence.
For the chapters on Old, Official and Middle Aramaic an effort was made to collect all known examples of verbs with objective suffixes. These forms are presented in charts found within each chapter. For the evidence of the Targums, of which Onqelos and Pseudo-Jonathan are used as representative, a sampling of examples is given. The Late Aramaic evidence is variously represented. Syriac and Mandaic, like the Targums, have too many examples of verbs with objective suffixes for a comprehensive list to be presented. Thus, only a sampling of forms is given in the charts. For the other dialects, examples were taken only from linguistically reliable texts. Babylonian Talmudic was not dealt with at all because of the unavailability, at this time, linguistically trustworthy material.
The extent and character of analysis of the various pronominal forms differ according to the nature of the preserved evidence. We have traced the phonological and morphological development of each suffix form and have tried to find a new explanation for other elements associated with the objective suffixes, in particular the "energic" nun. Problematic and noteworthy verbal forms are also discussed in detail.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Bennett, Stephan Frank. “Objective Pronominal Suffixes in Aramaic.” Ph.D. dissertation, Yale University, 1984.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Objective%20Pronominal%20Suffixes%20in%20Aramaic&amp;amp;rft.inst=Yale%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Stephan%20Frank&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Bennett&amp;amp;rft.au=Stephan%20Frank%20Bennett&amp;amp;rft.date=1984"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Stephan Frank Bennett, <title level="a">Objective Pronominal Suffixes in Aramaic</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, Yale University, 1984).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>