<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Eastern Christian Apocalyptic in the Early Muslim Period: Pseudo-Methodius and Pseudo-Athanasius</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/9E9DFXRT/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Francisco Javier</forename><surname>Martinez</surname></author><title level="m">Eastern Christian Apocalyptic in the Early Muslim Period: Pseudo-Methodius and Pseudo-Athanasius</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/9E9DFXRT</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/9E9DFXRT</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/9E9DFXRT</idno><imprint><date>1985</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The apocalyptic writings produced in the Christian East after the Muslim invasions are only partially known to scholars and little studied. The present dissertation edits two such writings, both from the Umayyad period. The Syriac Apocalypse of Pseudo-Methodius (chapter I), from the late VII century, is here edited for the first time from the text in MS Vat. Syr. 58. The text, which is not well preserved in the MS, is improved through a systematic comparison with the Greek and Latin versions of the work, and through recourse to other Syriac sources. An English version, with explanatory notes, accompanies the edition. Chapter II reedits a fragmentary Syriac apocalypse which was considered by its first editor to be the original form of the Syriac Pseudo- Methodius, but which may now be seen a late medieval reworking, probably from the Mongol period. Chapter III edits, also for the first time, the Sahidic Apocalypse of Pseudo-Athanasius, from MS Pierpont Morgan M 602 and the fragment from the Cairo Museum no. 9299, together with the Arabic version of it, based on MS Mingana Syr. 461 and MS Borgia Ar. 200. This Arabic version helps to fill the numerous lacunae in the Coptic text. The work is probably from the first decades of the VIII century. As in chapters I and II, English versions and explanatory notes are provided. These texts afford the scholar an insight into the earliest Christian reaction to the conquering Muslims.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Martinez, Francisco Javier. “Eastern Christian Apocalyptic in the Early Muslim Period: Pseudo-Methodius and Pseudo-Athanasius.” Ph.D. dissertation, The Catholic University of America, 1985.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Eastern%20Christian%20Apocalyptic%20in%20the%20Early%20Muslim%20Period%3A%20Pseudo-Methodius%20and%20Pseudo-Athanasius&amp;amp;rft.inst=The%20Catholic%20University%20of%20America&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Francisco%20Javier&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Martinez&amp;amp;rft.au=Francisco%20Javier%20Martinez&amp;amp;rft.date=1985&amp;amp;rft.tpages=637"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Francisco Javier Martinez, <title level="a">Eastern Christian Apocalyptic in the Early Muslim Period: Pseudo-Methodius and Pseudo-Athanasius</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, The Catholic University of America, 1985).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>