<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The Syriac Acts of Thomas: A Computerized Grammatical Concordance of Acts 1 and 2</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/AAVALUQW/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>John David</forename><surname>Zemler</surname></author><title level="m">The Syriac Acts of Thomas: A Computerized Grammatical Concordance of Acts 1 and 2</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/AAVALUQW</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/AAVALUQW</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/AAVALUQW</idno><imprint><date>2003</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">At present there is no concordance to the Syriac &lt;i&gt;Acts of Thomas&lt;/i&gt;. The lack of a concordance hobbles research into this early third-century Christian apocryphal acts. A Greek concordance already exists. In order to study the &lt;i&gt;Acts of Thomas&lt;/i&gt; with any confidence a concordance is necessary for both the Greek and the Syriac. Research interests in the &lt;i&gt;Acts&lt;/i&gt; revolve around a number of areas, including, but not limited to the following: (1) Translation Direction: The question concerning the &lt;i&gt;Acts&lt;/i&gt;' original language remains, was it Greek or Syriac? (2) Sacraments: The &lt;i&gt;Acts of Thomas&lt;/i&gt; offer insights from early Christianity concerning Baptism and Eucharist. (3) Biblical texts and Translations: The text retains readings which can be classified as belonging to the Old Syriac Gospels and possibly to the Diatesseron. (4) The Thomas Tradition: The &lt;i&gt;Acts&lt;/i&gt; are part of the Thomas Tradition. (5) Apocryphal Acts of the Apostles: The &lt;i&gt;Acts&lt;/i&gt; are one of the five great apocryphal acts of the apostles. (6) Gender Studies: Women play a crucial part in most of the individual stories which form the &lt;i&gt;Acts&lt;/i&gt;. (7) Jewish-Christian Relations: There appear to be connections between some portions of the &lt;i&gt;Acts&lt;/i&gt; and portions of the Talmud. None of these areas of research can be fully undertaken without a concordance to the Syriac &lt;i&gt;Acts of Thomas&lt;/i&gt;. To this end, I have automated the Syriac text of the &lt;i&gt;Acts of Thomas&lt;/i&gt; as found in the 1871 William Wright edition of the British Museum manuscript additional 14,645. I have developed a concordance which emphasizes automation and grammatical classification of the text. My aim is two-fold, to offer a grammatical concordance to Acts 1 and 2, and to exploit modern word processing software to be able to conduct this research without having to take courses in computer programming. Acts 1 and 2 circulated separately from the entire thirteen act version, so a concordance to those two acts will be immediately useful for research on the &lt;i&gt;Acts of Thomas&lt;/i&gt;.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Zemler, John David. “The Syriac Acts of Thomas: A Computerized Grammatical Concordance of Acts 1 and 2.” Ph.D. dissertation, Marquette University, 2003.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=The%20Syriac%20Acts%20of%20Thomas%3A%20A%20Computerized%20Grammatical%20Concordance%20of%20Acts%201%20and%202&amp;amp;rft.inst=Marquette%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=John%20David&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Zemler&amp;amp;rft.au=John%20David%20Zemler&amp;amp;rft.date=2003&amp;amp;rft.tpages=272"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">John David Zemler, <title level="a">The Syriac Acts of Thomas: A Computerized Grammatical Concordance of Acts 1 and 2</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, Marquette University, 2003).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>