<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">Conceptual and Terminological System of Abu Ra’ita at-Takriti</title><title level="j">Христианство на Ближнем Востоке</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/AJZICQK3/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2025-05-20-05:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2025-05-20-05:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="journalArticle"><analytic><author><forename>Oleg</forename><surname>Davydenkov</surname></author><title level="a">Conceptual and Terminological System of Abu Ra’ita at-Takriti</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/AJZICQK3</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/AJZICQK3</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/AJZICQK3</idno></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Христианство на Ближнем Востоке</title><textLang mainLang="Russian"/><biblScope unit="vol">8:2</biblScope><imprint><date>2024</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">99-114</biblScope></monogr><note type="abstract">Habib ibn Hidma Abu Ra’ita al-Takriti (first half of the 9th century) was the first Syro-Jacobite author who began to create theological works in Arabic. The importance of Abu Ra’ita for his community is quite comparable to that of the famous Theodore Abu Qurra for the Melkites. However, unlike the latter, Abu Ra’ita has been unjustifiably overlooked by scholars. Thus, to date there have been no works in which attempts were made to explore his theological terminology and Christological doctrine. There is not a single work in Russian dedicated to this Jacobite thinker. For a correct understanding of the theological thought of Arab Christian writers of both the 9th and subsequent centuries, it is necessary to understand the extent to which these thinkers acted as continuers of the theological traditions that had developed in their confessional groups at the time of the Arab conquest. In this article, an attempt has been made to reconstruct the conceptual and terminological system of Abu Ra’ita, a comparative analysis of the theological terminologies of Abu Ra’ita and the most prominent representatives of Greek moderate Monophysitism of the 6th century has been carried out, as a result of which it has been established that the common point for at-Takriti and the Greek Monophysites of the Severian trend is the philosophical premise of the fundamental impossibility of the complete actualization of the general in the particular (individual). It is precisely this premise that explains Abu Ra’ita’s rejection of the trinitarian teaching of the Melkites, with which he was familiar from the writings of Abu Qurra. The main difference should be recognized by Abu Ra’ita’s introduction of the concept of “substance” (ḏāt) into his system, which, being a connecting link between essence (ǧawhar) and hypostasis (individual), is meaningfully represents a combination of 1) quiddity (māhiyyah), that is, a particular copy of the common essence (ǧawhar ʿāmm); 2) the principle of actual existence as the opposite to non-existence; 3) the principle of particular substantial existence (qiwām ḏāt ḫāṣṣ), that is, separate and self-substantial being.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Davydenkov, Oleg. “Conceptual and Terminological System of Abu Ra’ita at-Takriti.” <title level="m">Христианство на Ближнем Востоке</title> 8:2 (2024): 99–114. https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.24412/2587-9316-2024-0080.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_id=info%3Adoi%2Fhttps%3A%2F%2Fdoi.org%2F10.24412%2F2587-9316-2024-0080&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Ajournal&amp;amp;rft.genre=article&amp;amp;rft.atitle=Conceptual%20and%20Terminological%20System%20of%20Abu%20Ra%E2%80%99ita%20at-Takriti&amp;amp;rft.jtitle=%D0%A5%D1%80%D0%B8%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B8%D0%B0%D0%BD%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B2%D0%BE%20%D0%BD%D0%B0%20%D0%91%D0%BB%D0%B8%D0%B6%D0%BD%D0%B5%D0%BC%20%D0%92%D0%BE%D1%81%D1%82%D0%BE%D0%BA%D0%B5&amp;amp;rft.volume=8%3A2&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Oleg&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Davydenkov&amp;amp;rft.au=Oleg%20Davydenkov&amp;amp;rft.date=2024&amp;amp;rft.pages=99-114&amp;amp;rft.spage=99&amp;amp;rft.epage=114&amp;amp;rft.language=Russian"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Oleg Davydenkov, <title level="a">Conceptual and Terminological System of Abu Ra’ita at-Takriti,</title> <title level="m">Христианство на Ближнем Востоке</title> 8:2 (2024): 99–114, https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.24412/2587-9316-2024-0080.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>