<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The Luminous Wind Fanned the East: A Comparative Study of the East Syriac Christian Documents in China (618–907)</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbssAU7MID6C/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2025-05-16-05:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2025-05-16-05:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Rong</forename><surname>Huang</surname></author><title level="m">The Luminous Wind Fanned the East: A Comparative Study of the East Syriac Christian Documents in China (618–907)</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbssAU7MID6C</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/AU7MID6C</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/AU7MID6C</idno><imprint><date>2024</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">This dissertation explores the Chinese manuscripts of East Syriac Christianity, also known as the Church of the East, during the Tang dynasty (618-907 CE) in China. Originating within the Sassanian Empire and driven by doctrinal disputes, this Christian tradition embarked on a journey eastward, eventually reaching Tang China via the Silk Road by the 7th century. Referred to as Jingjiao 景教 (Luminous Teaching) in Chinese, this form of Christianity took root within the cosmopolitan landscape of Tang China. By carefully analyzing the six Jingjiao texts discovered in Dunhuang, this dissertation sheds light on the missionary activities and theological adaptation of the Jingjiao community in Tang China.
Through an interdisciplinary approach, this dissertation investigates how Jingjiao missionaries, amidst dominant religious traditions such as Buddhism, Daoism, and Confucianism in Tang China, borrowed from Chinese religious vocabulary to convey Christian teachings effectively. An evolutionary trajectory can be discerned in the Jingjiao texts, from early Tang documents characterized by biblical content to late Tang manuscripts exhibiting a strong synthesis with Chinese religious thought. The authenticity of these texts, particularly the early Tang manuscripts, is scrutinized in light of contemporary scholarly debates, with arguments for their genuineness grounded in textual analysis and historical context.
This dissertation employs a comparative framework and draws on theories of translation studies and Paul Ricoeur’s theory of “threefold mimesis” to examine the intricate interplay between East Syriac Christianity and Chinese religious traditions during the Tang dynasty in China. Recognizing the necessity of understanding both the Chinese religious context and the East Syriac context, this study aims to elucidate how Jingjiao texts make the East Syriac theology intelligible to a Chinese audience while also preserving its Christian core.
Chapter 1 investigates the Early Tang Christian text &lt;i&gt;Discourse on the One God&lt;/i&gt; (Yishenlun 一神論), focusing on two terms—zhongxing 種性 (seed nature) and wuyin 五蔭 (five aggregates)—and their East Syriac theological implications such as the emphasis on human potentiality and the pedagogical and salvific purpose of the humanity of Christ. Chapter 2 analyzes the late Tang Jingjiao text &lt;i&gt;Book on Mysterious Peace and Joy&lt;/i&gt; (Zhixuan anle jing 志玄安樂經), exploring its key passages through both Chinese Buddhist and East Syriac ascetic lenses. Chapter 3 provides a comprehensive overview of theological themes in extant Jingjiao texts, highlighting such themes as the transcendence of God, Christ’s redemptive role, and ascetic practices. Chapter 4 incorporates archaeological findings of the Tang Jingjiao community and discusses its ascetic practices and distinct Sogdian influences.
Ultimately, this dissertation illuminates the complex interplay between East Syriac Christianity and Chinese religious traditions, underscoring the resilience and adaptability of the Jingjiao community in propagating its faith within the diverse cultural milieu of Tang China.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Huang, Rong. “The Luminous Wind Fanned the East: A Comparative Study of the East Syriac Christian Documents in China (618–907).” Ph.D. dissertation, Harvard University, 2024.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=The%20Luminous%20Wind%20Fanned%20the%20East%3A%20A%20Comparative%20Study%20of%20the%20East%20Syriac%20Christian%20Documents%20in%20China%20(618%E2%80%93907)&amp;amp;rft.inst=Harvard%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Rong&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Huang&amp;amp;rft.au=Rong%20Huang&amp;amp;rft.date=2024"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Rong Huang, <title level="a">The Luminous Wind Fanned the East: A Comparative Study of the East Syriac Christian Documents in China (618–907)</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, Harvard University, 2024).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>