<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">From Rome to Iran: Identity and Xusrō II</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/B8TI3JPW/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Keenan</forename><surname>Baca-Winters</surname></author><title level="m">From Rome to Iran: Identity and Xusrō II</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/B8TI3JPW</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/B8TI3JPW</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/B8TI3JPW</idno><imprint><date>2015</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The Roman-Sasanian War of the seventh century CE was the last conflict of late antiquity. Sahansah Xusro II nearly conquered the Roman Empire. James Howard-Johnston has studied the war extensively. Walter Kaegi has produced a biography of Xusro II's opponent, Heraclius, while Geoffrey Greatrex and Touraj Daryaee have written articles focusing on Xusro II. Scholars, however, have not attempted a major study of him. This dissertation seeks not only to understand how different authors depicted Xusro II but to understand the man's personality.
Roman authors who witnessed the war sought to highlight only the negative aspects of Xusro II. He was, according to the Romans, an enemy of God. Fear of Xusro II was the basis for these depictions. Pseudo-Sebeos, an Armenian historian, depicted Xusro II as an arrogant, blasphemous ruler. Pseudo-Sebeos, however, did not write anything positive about the Romans, either, because both the Romans and Sasanians wanted to control Armenia.
Christians living under Xusro II's rulership also seemed to despise him. They portray Xusro II as wicked because, in an attempt to punish them, he did not let allow them to elect a ruler. A careful reading of these sources, however, suggests these authors were aware of how Xusro II took care of Christians in his realm. Finally, Arab and Persian sources differ in their portrayals of Xusro II because both groups, although both Muslim, were competing for legitimacy in the post-Islamic conquest of Iran, due to ethnic tensions. Arab authors emphasized Xusro II's faults. Persian authors, on the other hand, presented his good qualities.
Ultimately, all of these different depictions of Xusro II demonstrate that he possessed a fierce will and embraced a vision of how to rule. Xusro II wanted to conquer the Romans and extend his domain and be remembered forever. Xusro II's drive might have made him seem arrogant to the authors studied in this dissertation, and they depicted him accordingly. We should not, however, lose sight of the man he truly was: a man who dared to dream.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Baca-Winters, Keenan. “From Rome to Iran: Identity and Xusrō II.” Ph.D. dissertation, University of California, Irvine, 2015.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=From%20Rome%20to%20Iran%3A%20Identity%20and%20Xusr%C5%8D%20II&amp;amp;rft.inst=University%20of%20California%2C%20Irvine&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Keenan&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Baca-Winters&amp;amp;rft.au=Keenan%20Baca-Winters&amp;amp;rft.date=2015"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Keenan Baca-Winters, <title level="a">From Rome to Iran: Identity and Xusrō II</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, University of California, Irvine, 2015).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>