<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The History of Tur Abdin</title><title level="s">Publications of the Archdiocese of the Syriac Orthodox Church in the Eastern United States 4</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/BVEFDA8N/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Ignatius Aphram</forename><surname>Barsoum</surname></author><translator><forename>Matti</forename><surname>Moosa</surname></translator><title level="m">The History of Tur Abdin</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/BVEFDA8N</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/BVEFDA8N</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/BVEFDA8N</idno><imprint><pubPlace>Piscataway, New Jersey</pubPlace><publisher>Gorgias Press</publisher><date>2008</date></imprint></monogr><series><title level="s">Publications of the Archdiocese of the Syriac Orthodox Church in the Eastern United States 4</title></series><note type="abstract">Translator's introduction --
Sources of this book --
Boundaries of the mountain (Tur Abdin), its people and name --
The introduction of Christianity to Tur Abdin --
Ascetics who flourished in the mountain (Tur Abdin) --
Fortresses of Tur Abdin --
Towns and villages of Tur Abdin --
Churches of Tur Abdin --
Monasteries of Tur Abdin --
The monastery of Qartmin --
Other patriarchs and maphrians of Tur Abdin --
Outstanding native bishops of Tur Abdin --
Bishops who flourished in Tur Abdin --
Bishops of Tur Abdin who sat in Hah --
Bishops of the monastery of Qartmin after the split of the diocese --
Native bishops of Tur Abdin who administered other dioceses --
Bishops of Tur Abdin in different times --
Bishops of other dioceses who came from Tur Abdin --
Patriarchs of Tur Abdin --
Illegitimate patriarch who sat in Tur Abdin, they are : Maphrians of Tur Abdin --
Bishops ordained by patriarchs of Tur Abdin each during his patriarchate --
Accounts of Syrian Church historians about the monastery of Qartmin --
Account of the historian monk of Qartmin --
Accounts of some ascetics, pious and venerable men who flourished in the monastery of Qartmin --
Account of the anonymous history published by Propus whose copy is in London no. 624/14 --
Account of Bar Hebraeus in his ecclesiastical history, part I --
Account of the historian Rabban Yeshu', Abbot of the Monastery of Qartmin (ascribed to Mar Dionysius Tall Mahre) --
Accounts we copied from the book of life of the monastery of Qartmin --
Books of the monastery's (of Qartmin) --
Other misfortunes which afflicted the monastery of Qartmin --
Accounts of Syrian historians about the affairs of Tur Abdin --
Account of Bar Hebraeus in his Syriac history --
Account of the historian Mar Mikhai'l al-Kabir (Michael Rabo, the Syrian) --
Account of the anonymous cleric of Edessa --
Account of the priest Addai of Basibrina around the year 1500 A.D., appended to the history of the learned Bar Hebraeus --
Travel of the priest Addai of Basibrina --
The warfare of Timur Khan (Tamerlane) in Tur Abdin taken from another copy --
The village of Basibrina --
Miscellaneous chronicles on Tur Abdin derived from ancient Syriac manuscripts preserved in churches and monasteries --
The Monastery of Mar Yaqub the Hermit in Salah --
The Monastery of Mar Gabriel (Qartmin) --
The Monastery of Mar Malke --
The Monastery of the Cross in Atafiya --
The Monastery of Mar Awgen --
The Monastery of Mar Sharbil --
Church of the Virgin in Midyat and other churches --
Ancient Syriac inscriptions in Tur Abdin on stones, tombs (epitaphs) and front doors of churches and monasteries --
The monastery of Qartmin --
The church of Mar Azazel in the village of Kafar ze --
The Church of Mar Cyriacus in Arnas --
The Church of Basibrina --
The Church of Hah --
The Church of Ishtarko (Heshtarke) --
The old Church of Mar Saba --
The ecession of Tur Abdin from the Apostolic see --
Dioceses of Tur Abdin --
Learned men and writers educated in Tur Abdin --
Syrian calligraphers of Tur Abdin --
Mar Shim'un (Simon) Zaytuni --
The family of Tuma Sharqi (Easterner) --
Family of the notable Saba of Basibrina --
The twelfth century 1110-1200? --
The Muhallamiyya --
Governors of Tur Abdin --
Ayyubid Kings (Lords) of Hisn Kifa --
Kurdish Bakhti rulers --
Manslaughter and devastation inflicted by Izz Al-Din Scher and Musawwar Beg in the year 1855 --
Warfare and calamities afflicting Tur Abdin --
Persecution of the Armeninas and Syrians in 1895 --
Vehement persecution (of the Christians) during world war I.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Barsoum, Ignatius Aphram. <title level="m">The History of Tur Abdin</title>. Translated by Matti Moosa. Publications of the Archdiocese of the Syriac Orthodox Church in the Eastern United States 4. Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2008.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Abook&amp;amp;rft.genre=book&amp;amp;rft.btitle=The%20History%20of%20Tur%20Abdin&amp;amp;rft.place=Piscataway%2C%20New%20Jersey&amp;amp;rft.publisher=Gorgias%20Press&amp;amp;rft.series=Publications%20of%20the%20Archdiocese%20of%20the%20Syriac%20Orthodox%20Church%20in%20the%20Eastern%20United%20States%204&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Ignatius%20Aphram&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Barsoum&amp;amp;rft.au=Ignatius%20Aphram%20Barsoum&amp;amp;rft.au=Matti%20Moosa&amp;amp;rft.date=2008"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Ignatius Aphram Barsoum, <title level="m">The History of Tur Abdin</title>, trans. Matti Moosa, Publications of the Archdiocese of the Syriac Orthodox Church in the Eastern United States 4 (Piscataway, New Jersey: Gorgias Press, 2008).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>