<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The Genesis and Exodus Citations of Aphrahat the Persian Sage</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/DMDTGKRP/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-06-17-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-06-17-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="thesis"><monogr><author><forename>Robert Jessen</forename><surname>Owens</surname></author><title level="m">The Genesis and Exodus Citations of Aphrahat the Persian Sage</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/DMDTGKRP</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/DMDTGKRP</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/DMDTGKRP</idno><imprint><date>1982</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">This study investigates the quotations of the biblical books of Genesis and Exodus that occur in the Demonstrations of Aphrahat the Persian Sage, a collection of twenty-three essays written in Syriac between A.D. 337 and 345. After a discussion of those features of the Demonstrations which encourage study of the bible quotations, previous scholarship is surveyed and detailed analysis is presented of past assessments of the Pentateuch quotations in the work of John Pinkerton, Anton Baumstark, and Arthur Voobus. The main body of the study reproduces the text of all the citations and allusions in the Demonstrations (a total of 221) that may provide evidence of the text of Genesis and Exodus known to Aphrahat. This is based on a fresh collation of the Syriac manuscripts of the Demonstrations. Each citation is analyzed and its value as a textual witness discussed. For each biblical verse that is attested, its affinities with and differences from the principal ancient bible versions are shown. The conclusion of the study is that, while Aphrahat's citations of Genesis and Exodus are not worthless as textual witnesses, caution must be exercised in using them, because Aphrahat often seems to quote inexactly. The evidence suggests a general habit of memoriter rather than transcriptional quotation. The most drastic departures from the Peshitta appear usually to result from casualness, intentional paraphrase, or error on Aphrahat's part rather than from a deviant scripture text. In those citations that appear to be literal, a somewhat ambiguous body of textual evidence is found. The vast majority of the citations agree with most or all of the Peshitta manuscripts and demonstrate that already in the fourth century Aphrahat knew a text of Genesis and Exodus that was essentially a Peshitta text. A small number of the citations, however, show affinities with one or more of the targums, the Septuagint, or the Vulgate. While these do not substantiate the theory of a wildly deviant, primitive Syriac text, they also fail to validate the view that Aphrahat knew a text that was much more literal to the Hebrew than the later Peshitta.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Owens, Robert Jessen. “The Genesis and Exodus Citations of Aphrahat the Persian Sage.” Ph.D. dissertation, The Johns Hopkins University, 1982.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=The%20Genesis%20and%20Exodus%20Citations%20of%20Aphrahat%20the%20Persian%20Sage&amp;amp;rft.inst=The%20Johns%20Hopkins%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Robert%20Jessen&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Owens&amp;amp;rft.au=Robert%20Jessen%20Owens&amp;amp;rft.date=1982&amp;amp;rft.tpages=290"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Robert Jessen Owens, <title level="a">The Genesis and Exodus Citations of Aphrahat the Persian Sage</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, The Johns Hopkins University, 1982).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/DMDTGKRP" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Aphrahat</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/DMDTGKRP" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Exodus</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/DMDTGKRP" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Genesis</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/DMDTGKRP" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>IV CE</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/DMDTGKRP" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Old Testament</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/DMDTGKRP" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Peshitta OT</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/DMDTGKRP" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>quotations</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>