<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Le village de Kafr ‘Aqāb: Étude monographique d’un site du ğebel Waṣṭāni (Massif calcaire de la Syrie du Nord). Topographie et architecture</title><title level="s">Bibliothèque de l’Antiquité Tardive 38</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/F6R7WV6S/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-15-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-15-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="book"><monogr><author><forename>Bertrand</forename><surname>Riba</surname></author><title level="m">Le village de Kafr ‘Aqāb: Étude monographique d’un site du ğebel Waṣṭāni (Massif calcaire de la Syrie du Nord). Topographie et architecture</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/F6R7WV6S</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/F6R7WV6S</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/F6R7WV6S</idno><imprint><pubPlace>Turnhout</pubPlace><publisher>Brepols</publisher><date>2018</date></imprint></monogr><series><title level="s">Bibliothèque de l’Antiquité Tardive 38</title></series><note type="abstract">The new monographic study of the village of Kafr ʿAqāb is a contribution to broadening the field of research into the western part of the Limestone Massif in Northern Syria which, until now, had been the subject of only limited interest. The ruins of the site are mainly spread out over a vast rocky headland which is strategically situated at the northern extremity of the ğebel Waṣṭāni near the Orontes valley in the inland region of Antioch. These ruins reveal the existence of an ancient village with over 80 homes, various communal constructions, a monastery, two ecclesiastic complexes and a fortified building.
The study is based on a detailed analysis of surface ruins and has enabled the evolution of the village to be precisely determined from its first phase of occupation between the second and third century until it was abandoned during the medieval period. Most of the constructions date from the Roman and Proto-Byzantine periods. Each architectural group (houses, tombs, churches, agricultural buildings, etc.) is studied separately then resituated in the context of the village and the region thus enabling the author to determine this peasant community’s economic, demographic, social and religious history.
Mechanisms linked to the growth of the locality are examined in the light of strategies implemented in the appropriation and enhancement of the surrounding land such as controlling water and the diversification of crops which reveals the inhabitants’ extraordinary capacity to adapt to their natural environment. Discussion also covers the question of the interactions between the villagers and their relationships with other towns. Kafr ʿAqāb also owed its prosperity to the road network which was ingeniously woven between towns as well as to its proximity to major urban areas in Antioche and Apamea. The ruins reveal this highly favourable location for trade and the circulation of various cultural and artistic movements. Finally, numerous archaeological signs allow the study of the occupation of the village after it was invaded by seventh century Arab conquerors. The author thus aims to reconstruct the history of this ancient site following a long and fascinating field study.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Riba, Bertrand. <title level="m">Le Village de Kafr ‘Aqāb: Étude Monographique d’Un Site Du Ğebel Waṣṭāni (Massif Calcaire de La Syrie Du Nord). Topographie et Architecture</title>. Bibliothèque de l’Antiquité Tardive 38. Turnhout: Brepols, 2018.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Abook&amp;amp;rft.genre=book&amp;amp;rft.btitle=Le%20village%20de%20Kafr%20%E2%80%98Aq%C4%81b%3A%20%C3%89tude%20monographique%20d%E2%80%99un%20site%20du%20%C4%9Febel%20Wa%E1%B9%A3%E1%B9%AD%C4%81ni%20(Massif%20calcaire%20de%20la%20Syrie%20du%20Nord).%20Topographie%20et%20architecture&amp;amp;rft.place=Turnhout&amp;amp;rft.publisher=Brepols&amp;amp;rft.series=Biblioth%C3%A8que%20de%20l%E2%80%99Antiquit%C3%A9%20Tardive%2038&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Bertrand&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Riba&amp;amp;rft.au=Bertrand%20Riba&amp;amp;rft.date=2018"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Bertrand Riba, <title level="m">Le Village de Kafr ‘Aqāb: Étude Monographique d’Un Site Du Ğebel Waṣṭāni (Massif Calcaire de La Syrie Du Nord). Topographie et Architecture</title>, Bibliothèque de l’Antiquité Tardive 38 (Turnhout: Brepols, 2018).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/F6R7WV6S" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Byzantine Syria</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/F6R7WV6S" ref="dc:subject"><desc>IV-VII CE</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/F6R7WV6S" ref="dc:subject"><desc>agriculture</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/F6R7WV6S" ref="dc:subject"><desc>archaeology</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/F6R7WV6S" ref="dc:subject"><desc>churches</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/F6R7WV6S" ref="dc:subject"><desc>demography</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/F6R7WV6S" ref="dc:subject"><desc>economics</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/F6R7WV6S" ref="dc:subject"><desc>monasteries</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/F6R7WV6S" ref="dc:subject"><desc>villages</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>