<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">Language, Literacy and Historical Apologetics: Hippolytus of Rome’s List of Literate Peoples in the Syriac Tradition</title><title level="j">Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/FB52JGR9/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><analytic><author><forename>Andy</forename><surname>Hilkens</surname></author><title level="a">Language, Literacy and Historical Apologetics: Hippolytus of Rome’s List of Literate Peoples in the Syriac Tradition</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/FB52JGR9</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/FB52JGR9</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/FB52JGR9</idno></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</title><biblScope unit="vol">72:1-2</biblScope><imprint><date>2020</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">1-32</biblScope></monogr><note type="abstract">In Late Antiquity and the Middle Ages, the Syriac language was part of several debates, including one about the identity of the language of Creation. Not surprisingly, many Syriac authors argued for the primacy of Aramaic over Hebrew. One genre of texts whose contribution to this debate has been neglected until now is that of lists of the literate peoples of the earth, categorized as descendants of Shem, Ham and Japheth. We encounter these lists, which are based on material that stems from the Greek chronicle tradition and that was eagerly appropriated by Syriac historical and exegetical authors, in manuscripts that date from the ninth to the nineteenth century. Sometimes they are transmitted independently, for instance under the name of Eusebius of Caesarea or Epiphanius of Salamis. Sometimes they are part of a larger context where more material on the division of the earth (the Diamerismos) was transmitted into Syriac. This article draws two important conclusions. First, a division can be made in the material between a conservative ‘Greek’ tradition, represented by the Chronicle of Michael the Elder (d. 1199 C.E.), and a progressive Syriac tradition. Several changes can be tracked, not only in the process of transmission from Greek into Syriac, but also an internal Syriac evolution. These lists were often updated, so much so that different traditions within the progressive Syriac tradition emerge. What connects the Syriac tradition, however, and this is the second conclusion that this study offers, is that the progressive Syriac tradition clearly offsets the Syriac language (or at least the written language that was used by the Syrians) against that of the Hebrews and the Greeks. Without explicitly going into the issue of the identity of the primeval language, these lists imply the old age of the Syriac language, similarly to Hebrew and Greek.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Hilkens, Andy. “Language, Literacy and Historical Apologetics: Hippolytus of Rome’s List of Literate Peoples in the Syriac Tradition.” <title level="m">Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</title> 72:1-2 (2020): 1–32.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Ajournal&amp;amp;rft.genre=article&amp;amp;rft.atitle=Language%2C%20Literacy%20and%20Historical%20Apologetics%3A%20Hippolytus%20of%20Rome%E2%80%99s%20List%20of%20Literate%20Peoples%20in%20the%20Syriac%20Tradition&amp;amp;rft.jtitle=Journal%20of%20Eastern%20Christian%20Studies&amp;amp;rft.volume=72%3A1-2&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Andy&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Hilkens&amp;amp;rft.au=Andy%20Hilkens&amp;amp;rft.date=2020&amp;amp;rft.pages=1-32&amp;amp;rft.spage=1&amp;amp;rft.epage=32"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Andy Hilkens, <title level="a">Language, Literacy and Historical Apologetics: Hippolytus of Rome’s List of Literate Peoples in the Syriac Tradition,</title> <title level="m">Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</title> 72:1-2 (2020): 1–32.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>