<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">The Terms οὐσία and φύσις and the Teaching on the “Double Consubstantiality” of Christ in the Theology of John of Caesarea and Severus of Antioch</title><title level="j">Богословский Вестник</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/FHM654Z4/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2025-05-20-05:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2025-05-20-05:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="journalArticle"><analytic><author><forename>Sergey A.</forename><surname>Kozhukhov</surname></author><title level="a">The Terms οὐσία and φύσις and the Teaching on the “Double Consubstantiality” of Christ in the Theology of John of Caesarea and Severus of Antioch</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/FHM654Z4</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/FHM654Z4</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/FHM654Z4</idno></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Богословский Вестник</title><textLang mainLang="Russian"/><biblScope unit="vol">3-4 [22-23]</biblScope><imprint><date>2016</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">129-146</biblScope></monogr><note type="abstract">The publication explores the problem aspects of the polemic between the followers of the Council of Chalcedon and its opponents concerning the understanding of the term “nature” and “essence”. In the IV century, thanks to the efforts of the first two Ecumenical councils and especially the Cappadocian Fathers the categories of the “common” and “particular” received their precise definitions. Closer to the end of the IV century these categories were uniquely used for expressing the category of “common” existence as opposed to “hypostasis” and “person”. After the Council of Chalcedon (451), during the polemic about the teaching of the “two natures” of Christ, the opponents of Chalcedon, to explain their monophysite teaching on the incarnation, invented a new interpretation of the category of “common” and “particular”. IT was Severus of Antioch who was it inventor, however is founded his ideas in an older tradition, which was based on the authority of Sts. Gregory the Theologian and Cyril of Alexandria. According to Severus the term “nature” must change its meaning of “common” and be used as a category of the “particular”, if one was to talk about the incarnation of the Son of God, while the term “essence” must express the abstract essence of the divine and humanity, having lost its connection with “nature”. Such a stance was necessitated by a resistance to accept two natures in Christ after the incarnation. This lead to controversies in the Trinitarian doctrine, which was always regarded be the Church Fathers as inseparable from the teaching of the incarnation. Severus’ adversary, the Chalcedonite John of Caesarea the Grammarian, juxtaposed Severus and the traditional understanding of Cappadocian terminology, together with the teachings of St. Cyril of Alexandria and the Council of Chalcedon.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Kozhukhov, Sergey A. “The Terms οὐσία and φύσις and the Teaching on the ‘Double Consubstantiality’ of Christ in the Theology of John of Caesarea and Severus of Antioch.” <title level="m">Богословский Вестник</title> 3-4 [22-23] (2016): 129–46.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Ajournal&amp;amp;rft.genre=article&amp;amp;rft.atitle=The%20Terms%20%CE%BF%E1%BD%90%CF%83%CE%AF%CE%B1%20and%20%CF%86%CF%8D%CF%83%CE%B9%CF%82%20and%20the%20Teaching%20on%20the%20%E2%80%9CDouble%20Consubstantiality%E2%80%9D%20of%20Christ%20in%20the%20Theology%20of%20John%20of%20Caesarea%20and%20Severus%20of%20Antioch&amp;amp;rft.jtitle=%D0%91%D0%BE%D0%B3%D0%BE%D1%81%D0%BB%D0%BE%D0%B2%D1%81%D0%BA%D0%B8%D0%B9%20%D0%92%D0%B5%D1%81%D1%82%D0%BD%D0%B8%D0%BA&amp;amp;rft.volume=3-4%20%5B22-23%5D&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Sergey%20A.&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Kozhukhov&amp;amp;rft.au=Sergey%20A.%20Kozhukhov&amp;amp;rft.date=2016&amp;amp;rft.pages=129-146&amp;amp;rft.spage=129&amp;amp;rft.epage=146&amp;amp;rft.language=Russian"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Sergey A. Kozhukhov, <title level="a">The Terms οὐσία and φύσις and the Teaching on the ‘Double Consubstantiality’ of Christ in the Theology of John of Caesarea and Severus of Antioch,</title> <title level="m">Богословский Вестник</title> 3-4 [22-23] (2016): 129–46.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>