<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">Images des anges dans l’enluminure syriaque de l’Antiquité tardive</title><title>Travaux et Mémoires 25.2</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/FVWGXJHK/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><analytic><author><forename>François</forename><surname>Pacha Miran</surname></author><title level="a">Images des anges dans l’enluminure syriaque de l’Antiquité tardive</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/FVWGXJHK</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/FVWGXJHK</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/FVWGXJHK</idno></analytic><monogr><editor><forename>Delphine</forename><surname>Lauritzen</surname></editor><title level="m">Inventer les anges de l’Antiquité à Byzance: conception, représentation, perception</title><imprint><pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace><publisher>Association des Amis du Centre d’Histoire et Civilisation de Byzance</publisher><date>2021</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">267-292</biblScope></monogr><series><title>Travaux et Mémoires 25.2</title></series><note type="abstract">Images of angels rarely appear in Late Antique Syriac manuscripts. Only two witnesses dating back to the 6th century contain such representations: Florence, Biblioteca Laurenziana, Cod. Plut. I 56, and Paris, Bibliothèque nationale de France, ms. syr. 33. Yet, the evidence of Syriac angels turns out to be essential to a better understanding of the formation and diffusion of iconographic patterns that marked Medieval art, such as the Annunciation and the Resurrection. These two manuscripts firstly attest the existence of a common visual language, shared among the Eastern Christian communities. The angels simultaneously adopt a role of messengers, witnesses, and heralds, that originates both in Christian literature and Classical art. The images also allow us to examine the different methods of layout and illustration used by Syriac artists, and the close relationships that linked the miniatures to the biblical texts. The presence of inscriptions on and around the miniatures reveals an astonishing concern for the creation of an ‘iconographic soundspace’. Through a careful depiction of the dialogues, the angels thereby embody the pronounced sensitivity of Syriac Christianity toward the written word and the dialogue. Between the lines, they finally evoke the vocal performance of hymns and canticles, sung during the main liturgical celebrations.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Pacha Miran, François. “Images Des Anges Dans l’enluminure Syriaque de l’Antiquité Tardive.” In <title level="m">Inventer Les Anges de l’Antiquité à Byzance: Conception, Représentation, Perception</title>, edited by Delphine Lauritzen, 267–92. Travaux et Mémoires 25.2. Paris: Association des Amis du Centre d’Histoire et Civilisation de Byzance, 2021.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Abook&amp;amp;rft.genre=bookitem&amp;amp;rft.atitle=Images%20des%20anges%20dans%20l%E2%80%99enluminure%20syriaque%20de%20l%E2%80%99Antiquit%C3%A9%20tardive&amp;amp;rft.btitle=Inventer%20les%20anges%20de%20l%E2%80%99Antiquit%C3%A9%20%C3%A0%20Byzance%3A%20conception%2C%20repr%C3%A9sentation%2C%20perception&amp;amp;rft.place=Paris&amp;amp;rft.publisher=Association%20des%20Amis%20du%20Centre%20d%E2%80%99Histoire%20et%20Civilisation%20de%20Byzance&amp;amp;rft.series=Travaux%20et%20M%C3%A9moires%2025.2&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Fran%C3%A7ois&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Pacha%20Miran&amp;amp;rft.au=Fran%C3%A7ois%20Pacha%20Miran&amp;amp;rft.au=Delphine%20Lauritzen&amp;amp;rft.date=2021&amp;amp;rft.pages=267-292&amp;amp;rft.spage=267&amp;amp;rft.epage=292"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">François Pacha Miran, <title level="a">Images Des Anges Dans l’enluminure Syriaque de l’Antiquité Tardive,</title> in <title level="m">Inventer Les Anges de l’Antiquité à Byzance: Conception, Représentation, Perception</title>, ed. Delphine Lauritzen, Travaux et Mémoires 25.2 (Paris: Association des Amis du Centre d’Histoire et Civilisation de Byzance, 2021), 267–92.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>