<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">A Philological Analysis of the Greek and the Syriac Texts of the Psalms of Solomon</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/G64WHZSD/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Grant</forename><surname>Ward</surname></author><title level="m">A Philological Analysis of the Greek and the Syriac Texts of the Psalms of Solomon</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/G64WHZSD</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/G64WHZSD</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/G64WHZSD</idno><imprint><date>1996</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The Psalms of Solomon are Jewish pseudepigraphical material from the late first century, B.C.E. surviving in eleven Greek and five Syriac texts dating from the eight to the sixteenth centuries C.E. They were included in the table of contents in the fifth century C.E. Codex Alexandrinus and continued to be copied and preserved and are important today for the light they shed on the historical and theological situation in the first century C.E. The focus of this dissertation is the demonstration of the probability of a Hebrew Vorlage behind both the Greek and the Syriac texts. Until recently, the scholarly consensus was that the Psalms were originally composed in Hebrew, translated into Greek and then into Syriac. Recently, there have been suggestions that both the Greek and the Syriac are translations of Hebrew and this dissertation in a thorough examination and comparison of the Greek and Syriac texts demonstrates a high degree of probability for this theory. Following the introduction and discussion of methodology (Chapter One) the bulk of the dissertation is a detailed examination of the eighteen psalms (Chapter Two) with a proposed Hebrew Vorlage and translation for the passages where the differences between the Greek and Syriac texts provides the clues for the original language. The conclusion (Chapter Three) also has some implications for further research in the Psalms of Solomon and other similar literature.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Ward, Grant. “A Philological Analysis of the Greek and the Syriac Texts of the Psalms of Solomon.” Ph.D. dissertation, Temple University, 1996.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=A%20Philological%20Analysis%20of%20the%20Greek%20and%20the%20Syriac%20Texts%20of%20the%20Psalms%20of%20Solomon&amp;amp;rft.inst=Temple%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Grant&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Ward&amp;amp;rft.au=Grant%20Ward&amp;amp;rft.date=1996&amp;amp;rft.tpages=305"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Grant Ward, <title level="a">A Philological Analysis of the Greek and the Syriac Texts of the Psalms of Solomon</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, Temple University, 1996).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>