<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The Syriac “Vita” Tradition of Ephrem the Syrian</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/GBDGBCZR/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-06-17-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-06-17-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="thesis"><monogr><author><forename>Joseph Phillip</forename><surname>Amar</surname></author><title level="m">The Syriac “Vita” Tradition of Ephrem the Syrian</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/GBDGBCZR</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/GBDGBCZR</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/GBDGBCZR</idno><idno type="deprecated">http://syriaca.org/bibl/2489</idno><idno type="deprecated">https://zotero.org/groups/392292/items/C8TKIE59</idno><imprint><date>1988</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">Ephrem the Syrian is the single most influential figure in the history of Syriac-speaking Christianity. His literary legacy testifies to catechetical, exegetical, and liturgical activities which had an inestimable impact on the churches of the Syrian East. In spite of the formative role he played, his Syriac Vita does not describe a man who is actively engaged in the life of the church. The Vita cultivates the figure of a recluse who shuns everyday life, and flees to the solitude of his cave to pursue solitary asceticism. This image projected by the Vita stands in stark contrast to the prominent figure whose literary compositions constituted a public event in the life of the church. In order to view the process which turned the Ephrem of history into an ideal of monastic piety, the three extant recensions of the SyriacVita have been broken down into pericopes, and compared synoptically. We discover that the earliest written reports regarding Ephrem originate among Greek-speaking ecclesiastical historians (Palladius, Socrates, Sozomen, Theodoret) who wrote from their own perspective of the monastic-inspired ideal. While these historians may have known something of Ephrem's wide-ranging literary activity through translations of his works into Greek, they wrote as observers who had no knowledge of the unique Semitic Christian context of Ephrem's life and times. The image of Ephrem contained in their accounts is enhanced and validated by the inclusion of anecdotes (apophthegmata) which are intended to indicate early signs or divine favor and election. A further source of cultural transference is traced to the operative Syriac term ihidaya ('single,' 'alone') which was translated as monachos, a word in Greek ascetical literature which designated someone who lived apart from society as a monk. In Ephrem's time, a period identified by scholars as 'premonastic,' the Syriac term designated someone who simply had taken a vow of celibacy, but who did not withdraw from active life in the world. Two recensions of the Vita (Vat. Syr. 117 and Par. Syr. 235) have been previously published, but neither edition is entirely faithful to the manuscripts. In the case of Vat. Syr. 117, Assemani's edition radically alters and re-writes the manuscript evidence. The present edition makes available for the first time the texts of all three recensions (Vat. Syr. 117, Par. Syr. 235, and BL 9384) of the Syriac Vita as they exist in the manuscripts.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Amar, Joseph Phillip. “The Syriac ‘Vita’ Tradition of Ephrem the Syrian.” Ph.D. dissertation, The Catholic University of America, 1988.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=The%20Syriac%20%E2%80%9CVita%E2%80%9D%20Tradition%20of%20Ephrem%20the%20Syrian&amp;amp;rft.inst=The%20Catholic%20University%20of%20America&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Joseph%20Phillip&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Amar&amp;amp;rft.au=Joseph%20Phillip%20Amar&amp;amp;rft.date=1988&amp;amp;rft.tpages=344"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Joseph Phillip Amar, <title level="a">The Syriac ‘Vita’ Tradition of Ephrem the Syrian</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, The Catholic University of America, 1988).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/GBDGBCZR" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Ephrem</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/GBDGBCZR" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Ephremiana [Syriac]</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/GBDGBCZR" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Vita Ephremi</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/GBDGBCZR" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>hagiography</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/GBDGBCZR" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>primary sources [Syriac] + English translation</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/GBDGBCZR" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>saints</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>