<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Fishers of Men: The Jesuits in Bilad al-Sham, 1625–1660</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/GYGUT6IW/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-15-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-15-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="thesis"><monogr><author><forename>Mazin</forename><surname>Tadros</surname></author><title level="m">Fishers of Men: The Jesuits in Bilad al-Sham, 1625–1660</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/GYGUT6IW</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/GYGUT6IW</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/GYGUT6IW</idno><imprint><date>2009</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">For several decades historians have struggled with the dynamics of cross-cultural contact and the creation of perceptions of the "other". Detailed studies of the European image of the Islamicate world during the pre-modern period rarely analyze why and how these representations were formed. Through the analysis of Jesuit missionary correspondences made during the first half of the seventeenth century, this study aims to articulate the variables that impacted the development of Jesuit attitudes toward the people and environment of Greater Syria. Jesuit written sources conveyed the challenges to the mission that arose from a multiplicity of sources, including from fellow Europeans, lay and religious alike. Their greatest challenge however was to understand, and insert themselves in, the cultural and doctrinal traditions of the indigenous population, Christian and Muslim. The tensions and opportunities experienced by the Jesuits, combined with their individual personalities and group mentalities, formed the basis of their views and impressions of Bilad al-Sham. Yet, equally as important in the understanding of the development of Jesuit perceptions, is the recognition that the medium of correspondence (letters, reports, or published works) had recognizable impact on the articulation of Jesuit experiences. As this study demonstrates, the level of objectivity in the expressions of the Jesuits depended on the form of communication they used. In their letters to their fellow priests in Europe, they showed ideological and cultural detachment, whereas in their published works they tended to include embellished stories and tropes familiar to their reading audience in Europe. Moreover, this study is an entrée into Jesuit mentalities and how they acted in and reacted to the prevailing political, social, and, cultural circumstances in Greater Syria between 1625 and 1660.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Tadros, Mazin. “Fishers of Men: The Jesuits in Bilad al-Sham, 1625–1660.” Ph.D. dissertation, State University of New York at Albany, 2009.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Fishers%20of%20Men%3A%20The%20Jesuits%20in%20Bilad%20al-Sham%2C%201625%E2%80%931660&amp;amp;rft.inst=State%20University%20of%20New%20York%20at%20Albany&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Mazin&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Tadros&amp;amp;rft.au=Mazin%20Tadros&amp;amp;rft.date=2009"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Mazin Tadros, <title level="a">Fishers of Men: The Jesuits in Bilad al-Sham, 1625–1660</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, State University of New York at Albany, 2009).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/GYGUT6IW" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Muslim-Christian relations</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/GYGUT6IW" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Roman Catholic</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/GYGUT6IW" ref="dc:subject"><desc>VII-XVIII CE</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/GYGUT6IW" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Western mission</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/GYGUT6IW" ref="dc:subject"><desc>XVII CE</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>