<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Pseudo-Clementine ‘Recognitions’ 1.27-71: Early Jewish Christian Perspectives on the Nature and History of Christianity</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/HN7R4ULE/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-15-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-15-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="thesis"><monogr><author><forename>Frederick Stanley</forename><surname>Jones</surname></author><title level="m">Pseudo-Clementine ‘Recognitions’ 1.27-71: Early Jewish Christian Perspectives on the Nature and History of Christianity</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/HN7R4ULE</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/HN7R4ULE</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/HN7R4ULE</idno><imprint><date>1989</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The Pseudo-Clementine Recognitions 1.27-71 are examined here as a source for early Jewish Christian perspectives on the nature and history of Christianity. Chapter 1 reviews previous scholarship and thereby discloses possibilities for interpretation. Though one scholar’s position has become dominant in modern times, it has not been thoroughly examined. Furthermore, the Syriac translation of the text has been neglected in favor of Rufinus’s Latin rendering. Chapter 2 addresses this problem of evaluating the two extant ancient translations of the lost Greek Recognitions. Rufinus’s theory of translation and his comments on his rendering of the Pseudo-Clementines are investigated. Recently discovered Armenian fragments and other acknowledged criteria reveal that while each of the two translations has its own peculiar shortcomings, they are of approximately the same accuracy.  Chapter 3 provides the first modern complete translation of the Syriac of Recognitions 1.27-71. Chapter 4 addresses the widely held thesis that this material is based on a special source. The literary place of this passage in the Recognitions and in the lost basic writing is identified, and the redaction of each author is isolated. Since the views of the remaining material differ from what is elsewhere attributable to the basic writing, this material seems indeed to derive from a special source. The limits of this source are identified as Recognitions 1.27.1-44.1, 53.4-71.6. Examination of this material reveals that its author, writing under the name of Matthew, employed the Greek Old Testament, the Book of Jubilees, Matthew, Luke, Acts, Hegesippus, Justin, and possibly the Gospel of the Ebionites. While some Jewish Christian themes are shared with the Anabathmoi Jakobou, evidence for dependency on this writing is insufficient. Chapter 5 concludes that the author is a Jewish Christian of about 200 C.E. He values astrology, sees Christianity as true Judaism, and is concerned with the Christian inheritance of the land of Israel. He possibly writes as a Jewish Christian presbyter or bishop in Jerusalem or Judaea.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Jones, Frederick Stanley. “Pseudo-Clementine ‘Recognitions’ 1.27-71: Early Jewish Christian Perspectives on the Nature and History of Christianity.” Ph.D. dissertation, Vanderbilt University, 1989.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Pseudo-Clementine%20%E2%80%98Recognitions%E2%80%99%201.27-71%3A%20Early%20Jewish%20Christian%20Perspectives%20on%20the%20Nature%20and%20History%20of%20Christianity&amp;amp;rft.inst=Vanderbilt%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Frederick%20Stanley&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Jones&amp;amp;rft.au=Frederick%20Stanley%20Jones&amp;amp;rft.date=1989&amp;amp;rft.tpages=229"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Frederick Stanley Jones, <title level="a">Pseudo-Clementine ‘Recognitions’ 1.27-71: Early Jewish Christian Perspectives on the Nature and History of Christianity</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, Vanderbilt University, 1989).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/HN7R4ULE" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Jewish Christianity</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/HN7R4ULE" ref="dc:subject"><desc>NT apocrypha</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/HN7R4ULE" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Pseudo-Clementines</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/HN7R4ULE" ref="dc:subject"><desc>primary sources [Syriac] - English translation</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>