<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Les églises et monastères du “Kurdistan irakien” à la veille et au lendemain de l’Islam</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/IEGRPB55/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Narmen Ali</forename><surname>Muhamad Amen</surname></author><title level="m">Les églises et monastères du “Kurdistan irakien” à la veille et au lendemain de l’Islam</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/IEGRPB55</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/IEGRPB55</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/IEGRPB55</idno><imprint><date>2001</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">Through this subject, we studied Christian art since before the advent of Islam (i.e. before the VIIth century) until the XIXth century, and the place of this art in Northern Mesopotamian art. Our study comprises five main parts. In the first part, we present the geographical and historical data of the region. Then we review the leading European travellers who travelled to and through Kurdistan between the XIIIth and XIXth centuries A.D. There were many of them, from Marco Polo to Mrs G. Bell. Their interests were quite varied and did not focus only on archeology : Mr Fiey, Mr Preusser and Mrs G. Bell, in particular, wrote remarkable works on Christian art in Kurdistan. In the second part, we study the basis of the general history of Christianity in Kurdistan and of the Sassanid period, during which the Nestorian Church of the Orient was born. We also examine the Arab conquest and the Kurds, the situation of the non Moslem communities under Arab domination, and the state of the churches and monasteries. In the third part, we study most of the churches and monasteries of Iraqi Kurdistan ; some of them had aready been studied by others, but we look at their present state. For the churches or monasteries which were less well or not known, we copied out their plan. Large parts of such work is devoted to their situation, their history and their architecture. A small number of convents which have remained intact are located in the Mossoul region.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Muhamad Amen, Narmen Ali. “Les Églises et Monastères Du ‘Kurdistan Irakien’ à La Veille et Au Lendemain de l’Islam.” Thèse de doctorat, Université de Saint-Quentin-en-Yvelines, 2001.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Les%20%C3%A9glises%20et%20monast%C3%A8res%20du%20%E2%80%9CKurdistan%20irakien%E2%80%9D%20%C3%A0%20la%20veille%20et%20au%20lendemain%20de%20l%E2%80%99Islam&amp;amp;rft.inst=Universit%C3%A9%20de%20Saint-Quentin-en-Yvelines&amp;amp;rft.degree=Th%C3%A8se%20de%20doctorat&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Narmen%20Ali&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Muhamad%20Amen&amp;amp;rft.au=Narmen%20Ali%20Muhamad%20Amen&amp;amp;rft.date=2001"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Narmen Ali Muhamad Amen, <title level="a">Les Églises et Monastères Du ‘Kurdistan Irakien’ à La Veille et Au Lendemain de l’Islam</title> (Thèse de doctorat, Université de Saint-Quentin-en-Yvelines, 2001).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>