<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Sogdiana, its Christians and Byzantium: A Study of Artistic and Cultural Connections in Late Antiquity and Early Middle Ages</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/IP74B3JK/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Aleksandr</forename><surname>Naymark</surname></author><title level="m">Sogdiana, its Christians and Byzantium: A Study of Artistic and Cultural Connections in Late Antiquity and Early Middle Ages</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/IP74B3JK</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/IP74B3JK</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/IP74B3JK</idno><imprint><date>2001</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The great geopolitical changes of the 3rd century C.E. gave a special importance to the branch of the Silk Road running through Soghd (Zarafshan and Kashka-darya Valleys in modern Uzbeksitan, Central Asia). By the early 5th century Sogdians were responsible for a large share of transactions in the Eurasian long distance trade. On the one hand, the extremely high profits from this trade fostered rapid urban development in Soghd and the formation of a rich merchant class with demand for various cultural novelties. On the other hand, the international trade brought the Sogdians into close contact with various civilizations and in particular with the Mediterranean world. The result was the intensive growth of the Late Roman and Early Byzantine component in Sogdian culture. A large Christian community, which simultaneously formed in Soghd served as a conductor of Western artistic ideas.
Discussing particular monuments of architecture, wall paintings, metalwork, ceramics and coins, this dissertation tries to answer the questions: How significant was the Early Christian/Byzantine influence on the Sogdian art? How did it enter Sogdiana? Which mechanisms were responsible for the absorption of the Late Antique and Byzantine elements in Sogdian art? The analysis takes into consideration the broad cultural context and involves various kinds of documentary and narrative sources. The results of this research testify for the greater role of Early Christian and Byzantine art in the development of Sogdian artistic tradition and allow us to see its influence in the monuments that are usually considered purely local in iconography and style.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Naymark, Aleksandr. “Sogdiana, Its Christians and Byzantium: A Study of Artistic and Cultural Connections in Late Antiquity and Early Middle Ages.” Ph.D. dissertation, Indiana University, 2001.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Sogdiana%2C%20its%20Christians%20and%20Byzantium%3A%20A%20Study%20of%20Artistic%20and%20Cultural%20Connections%20in%20Late%20Antiquity%20and%20Early%20Middle%20Ages&amp;amp;rft.inst=Indiana%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Aleksandr&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Naymark&amp;amp;rft.au=Aleksandr%20Naymark&amp;amp;rft.date=2001"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Aleksandr Naymark, <title level="a">Sogdiana, Its Christians and Byzantium: A Study of Artistic and Cultural Connections in Late Antiquity and Early Middle Ages</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, Indiana University, 2001).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>