<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The Psalm-Commentary of Dionysius bar Salibi</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/K6DKX9TJ/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-06-17-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-06-17-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="thesis"><monogr><author><forename>Marjorie Helen</forename><surname>Simpkin</surname></author><title level="m">The Psalm-Commentary of Dionysius bar Salibi</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/K6DKX9TJ</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/K6DKX9TJ</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/K6DKX9TJ</idno><imprint><date>1974</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The present dissertation consists of a detailed investigation of the commentary of Dionysius bar Salibi on Psalms 1-72. To begin with, the commentary is considered in its historical setting. Dionysius bar Salibi was a bishop in the Syrian Jacobite Church of the mid-twelfth century A.D. In a period marked by natural calamities and political and religious conflict, bar Salibi was an upright and strong leader of his people. His concern for integrity and moral rectitude among his parishioners and disciples is evident throughout the commentary. This strong ethical emphasis is combined with pastoral encouragement and comfort for those in need.
An investigation of the liturgical setting of the Psalm-commentary has shown that the words of the Psalms provided a ready source for the composition of the prayers in the Jacobite liturgy. They also have an important place in the Daily Offices of the Church. The use of the Psalms in the Church's liturgies has strongly influenced the exposition of the Psalms in bar Salibi's commentary. Although a wider community no doubt shared in the Eucharistic Liturgy, the Hours of Prayer were largely celebrated by the monks and those seeking to join monastic communities. It was in the monasteries and schools that the Psalms gained a position of considerable importance, forming a basic part of the curriculum, and the fundamental ingredient of private devotions. It is suggested that Dionysius bar Salibi had people such as these monks in view as he wrote the Psalm-commentary.
Dionysius did not claim originality for the ideas presented in his commentary. He saw his task as that of distilling from the works of previous writers the best teaching for the benefit of the people of his own day. Some of his sources he named, others he did not, but there is no simple formula to describe the origins of his work. The version of Scripture most frequently used in bar Salibi’s commentary is the Peshitta, though the Syro-Hexaplar is also quoted, as well as several other forms of the text.
The Psalm-commentary, like all of bar Salibi's Old Testament comrnentaries, consists of two parts. In the "literal” commentary, the shorter of the two, the author generally interprets the Psalms in a historical sense, applying them to David, or some other person or occasion in Israel's history. The "spiritual" commentary has a much fuller, more homiletic character, and usually provides a Christological explanation of the Psalms. In fact, Christ is seen as the major subject of the Psalms which are used as a vehicle to convey the Church's doctrines about Man and God, and in particular about Jesus Christ.
Finally an analysis of the extant MSS of this commentary was undertaken by the construction of a sample critical text, and the results evaluated.
As a result of this investigation, the Sitz im Leben of the Psalm-commentary of Dionysius bar Salibi has been recognised in broad outline, and hence its general significance can be more clearly defined.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Simpkin, Marjorie Helen. “The Psalm-Commentary of Dionysius Bar Salibi.” Ph.D. dissertation, University of Melbourne, 1974.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=The%20Psalm-Commentary%20of%20Dionysius%20bar%20Salibi&amp;amp;rft.inst=University%20of%20Melbourne&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Marjorie%20Helen&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Simpkin&amp;amp;rft.au=Marjorie%20Helen%20Simpkin&amp;amp;rft.date=1974"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Marjorie Helen Simpkin, <title level="a">The Psalm-Commentary of Dionysius Bar Salibi</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, University of Melbourne, 1974).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/K6DKX9TJ" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Dionysius bar Salibhi</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/K6DKX9TJ" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Jacobites</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/K6DKX9TJ" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Old Testament</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/K6DKX9TJ" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Psalms</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/K6DKX9TJ" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>VII-XVIII CE</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/K6DKX9TJ" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>XII CE</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/K6DKX9TJ" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>commentary</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/K6DKX9TJ" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>exegesis</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/K6DKX9TJ" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>primary sources [Syriac] + English translation</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>