<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The Christology of Theodore of Mopsuestia as Expressed in the Greek Fragments of his &lt;i&gt;Commentarius in Evangelium Ioannis Apostoli&lt;/i&gt;</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/LMSIC5BK/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-15-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-15-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="thesis"><monogr><author><forename>George</forename><surname>Kalantzis</surname></author><title level="m">The Christology of Theodore of Mopsuestia as Expressed in the Greek Fragments of his &lt;i&gt;Commentarius in Evangelium Ioannis Apostoli&lt;/i&gt;</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/LMSIC5BK</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/LMSIC5BK</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/LMSIC5BK</idno><imprint><date>1997</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The focus of this study is the Christology of Theodore, the bishop of Mopsuestia (ca. 352-428), as is expressed in the Greek fragments of his &lt;i&gt;Commentary on John&lt;/i&gt;. (In addition, I provide as an appendix an English translation of critical edition of 'Les Fragments grecs du commaintaire sur le quatrieme evangile, Appendix in Essai sur Theodore de Mopsueste, Vol. 141, Studi e Testi, Vatican, 1948.) Chapter One explores briefly Theodore's life, his place in the life and conscience of the Eastern Syriac Church and the history of his condemnation. The recent scholarship and discussion on his Christology are also examined. Chapter Two examines the traditional approaches to interpreting Theodore's Christology, especially those of Cyril of Alexandria, Leontius of Byzantium and the Constitutum Vigilii, as well as the Acts of the Council of the Three Chapters. This analysis shows that the three main accusations brought against Theodore were that he was teaching a Nestorian Christology of Duo Filii, a lack of Communicatio Idiomatum, and the mutability of the Incarnate Logos. Chapter Three examines the place of the Commentary in the literary activity of its author as well as the history of its translation and transmission up to the critical edition of 1948. Chapter Four carefully analyzes the Greek fragments of the Commentary on John and reveals that they do not support the conclusion to which Cyril and the Council came. This analysis reveals that in the Greek fragments of his Commentary on John, Theodore exhibited a clear unity of person in the Incarnate Logos, placing great emphasis in presenting and promoting the Nicene-Constantinopolitan understanding of the homoousian relationship between Father and Son in reaction to Arian and Apollinarian thought. It also reveals that Theodore's Christology did contain a Communicatio Idiomatum, though his model (in concreto) was quite different from that of Athanasius and Cyril. Lastly, this analysis shows that, in accordance with the Nicene anathemas of 325, Theodore insisted on the immutable character of the Incarnation, as related to the nature of the Logos, ascribing transformation into incorruptibility only to the post-Resurrection body of Christ.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Kalantzis, George. “The Christology of Theodore of Mopsuestia as Expressed in the Greek Fragments of His <title level="m">Commentarius in Evangelium Ioannis Apostoli</title>.” Ph.D. dissertation, Northwestern University, 1997.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=The%20Christology%20of%20Theodore%20of%20Mopsuestia%20as%20Expressed%20in%20the%20Greek%20Fragments%20of%20his%20%3Ci%3ECommentarius%20in%20Evangelium%20Ioannis%20Apostoli%3C%2Fi%3E&amp;amp;rft.inst=Northwestern%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=George&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Kalantzis&amp;amp;rft.au=George%20Kalantzis&amp;amp;rft.date=1997&amp;amp;rft.tpages=554"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">George Kalantzis, <title level="a">The Christology of Theodore of Mopsuestia as Expressed in the Greek Fragments of His Commentarius in Evangelium Ioannis Apostoli</title>” (Ph.D. dissertation, Northwestern University, 1997).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/LMSIC5BK" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Antiochene school</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/LMSIC5BK" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Christology</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/LMSIC5BK" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Gospel of John</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/LMSIC5BK" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Gospels</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/LMSIC5BK" ref="dc:subject"><desc>New Testament</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/LMSIC5BK" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Theodore of Mopsuestia</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/LMSIC5BK" ref="dc:subject"><desc>V CE</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/LMSIC5BK" ref="dc:subject"><desc>commentary</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/LMSIC5BK" ref="dc:subject"><desc>exegesis</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/LMSIC5BK" ref="dc:subject"><desc>primary sources [Greek] + English translation</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>