<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">“Histoire et Sagesse d’Aḥiqar l’Assyrien” ou l’Ummānu sans descendance: invariance et variations, de l’Antiquité au XVIII&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; siècle</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/LVPPZEQW/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Laurent</forename><surname>Karouby</surname></author><title level="m">“Histoire et Sagesse d’Aḥiqar l’Assyrien” ou l’Ummānu sans descendance: invariance et variations, de l’Antiquité au XVIII&lt;sup&gt;e&lt;/sup&gt; siècle</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/LVPPZEQW</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/LVPPZEQW</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/LVPPZEQW</idno><imprint><date>2013</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">“History and wisdom Aḥiqar the Assyrian” is an exception text since its roots goes in the ancient times of ancient Mesopotamia. His hero, Ahiqar is a Sage, a Ummānu, advise the kings of Assyria, and he is the subject of a vile plot, hatched by his nephew that the Sage had yet raised as if he were her own son ; from the brink of death, Ahiqar is rehabilitated and sent to Egypt to confront the puzzles and the challenges that the Pharaoh launched against his king, while his nephew is punished by death. Our text corpus has seven versions of “History and wisdom Ahiqar the Assyrian,” ranging from 500 BC until the eighteenth century, and composed in Aramaic, in Syriac, in Ge’ez, in Arabic and in Greek. In a comparison conducted in French translation, through the versions we have and all along the different episodes of the story, we first study the dramatic trajectory of life Ahiqar. We then examine the puzzles and challenges addressed by this expert hero of language against Pharaoh before analyzing the two long series of maxims, first educational and punitive, that it administers to his nephew. We also discuss the terms of re-use, or how the history of Aramaic Ahiqar could be re-used, with more or less success, in the Bible, the “Book of Tobit” in the “Life of Aesop the Phrygian” famous Greek fabulist, and the world of “Arabian Nights” with the tale entitled “Sinkarib and two viziers.” Finally, we conclude on the interest of this great figure of Ummānu or advise the king - nor a warrior hero, nor a saint hero, but a language man - for the history of rhetoric.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Karouby, Laurent. “‘Histoire et Sagesse d’Aḥiqar l’Assyrien’ Ou l’Ummānu sans Descendance: Invariance et Variations, de l’Antiquité Au XVIIIe Siècle.” Thèse de doctorat, Aix-Marseille Université, 2013.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=%E2%80%9CHistoire%20et%20Sagesse%20d%E2%80%99A%E1%B8%A5iqar%20l%E2%80%99Assyrien%E2%80%9D%20ou%20l%E2%80%99Umm%C4%81nu%20sans%20descendance%3A%20invariance%20et%20variations%2C%20de%20l%E2%80%99Antiquit%C3%A9%20au%20XVIII%3Csup%3Ee%3C%2Fsup%3E%20si%C3%A8cle&amp;amp;rft.inst=Aix-Marseille%20Universit%C3%A9&amp;amp;rft.degree=Th%C3%A8se%20de%20doctorat&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Laurent&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Karouby&amp;amp;rft.au=Laurent%20Karouby&amp;amp;rft.date=2013"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Laurent Karouby, <title level="a">‘Histoire et Sagesse d’Aḥiqar l’Assyrien’ Ou l’Ummānu sans Descendance: Invariance et Variations, de l’Antiquité Au XVIIIe Siècle</title> (Thèse de doctorat, Aix-Marseille Université, 2013).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>