<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Exploring the Harbor of Rest: The Significance of ἀνάπαυσις in the Theology of the Pseudo-Macarian Corpus</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/N3UR76AU/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Susan E.</forename><surname>Ramsey</surname></author><title level="m">Exploring the Harbor of Rest: The Significance of ἀνάπαυσις in the Theology of the Pseudo-Macarian Corpus</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/N3UR76AU</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/N3UR76AU</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/N3UR76AU</idno><imprint><date>2012</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">This dissertation explores the use of 'Rest' (ἀνάπαυσις) terminology in the Pseudo-Macarian Corpus, dating between 370 and 420 CE in the region of Syro-Mesopotamia or Asia Minor. The study examines the ways that Pseudo-Macarius uses this significant terminology in the three primary collections of the Macarian Corpus and how 'Rest' relates to his overarching theological vision. The author of the Macarian Corpus draws from a variety of traditions and this study examines how those sources inform his theology. The theme of Rest serves as both the root and apex of his reflections on the nature of humanity, his understanding of Jesus Christ and the Holy Spirit, the need for entering into the spiritual combat, and the Sabbath. Finally, this dissertation searches for contributions that Macarius' view of 'Rest' could make to the contemporary discussion of Sabbath.
Using the Thesaurus Linguae Graecae database, the citations of 'Rest' in the three major collections of the Macarian Corpus were identified. These passages were then examined for theological themes and analyzed for their significance for Macarian theology. For each major topic, the historical developments and contemporaneous views were researched and included in the study.
This analysis revealed that: 1) Rest is absolutely central to the theology of the Macarian Corpus. 2) Earlier scholars who detected the importance of Rest in the Macariana were correct, although this topic had remained unexplored. 3) Macarius draws from a variety of sources and these sources are detectable in his use of Rest. 4) Rest terminology grew rapidly in usage from the second century BCE to the fourth century CE. 5) Rest is a key theological and liturgical theme in Syrian Christianity. 6) Rest is connected to the imago Dei and biblical anthropomorphism. 7) Rest is connected to a nexus of themes related to ἔρως and nuptial imagery. 8) Macarius draws upon the earlier melding of Sabbath as divine time and Sanctuary as divine dwelling place that began with the Songs of Sabbath Sacrifice and the Epistle to the Hebrews. 9) The Macarian understanding of Rest adds an important voice to the contemporary discussion of the meaning of Sabbath.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Ramsey, Susan E. “Exploring the Harbor of Rest: The Significance of Ἀνάπαυσις in the Theology of the Pseudo-Macarian Corpus.” Ph.D. dissertation, Marquette University, 2012.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Exploring%20the%20Harbor%20of%20Rest%3A%20The%20Significance%20of%20%E1%BC%80%CE%BD%CE%AC%CF%80%CE%B1%CF%85%CF%83%CE%B9%CF%82%20in%20the%20Theology%20of%20the%20Pseudo-Macarian%20Corpus&amp;amp;rft.inst=Marquette%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Susan%20E.&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Ramsey&amp;amp;rft.au=Susan%20E.%20Ramsey&amp;amp;rft.date=2012"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Susan E. Ramsey, <title level="a">Exploring the Harbor of Rest: The Significance of Ἀνάπαυσις in the Theology of the Pseudo-Macarian Corpus</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, Marquette University, 2012).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>