<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Translation Technique in the Peshitta of the Book of Micah</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/NF3JPQYS/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-15-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-15-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="thesis"><monogr><author><forename>Dennis Robert</forename><surname>Magary</surname></author><title level="m">Translation Technique in the Peshitta of the Book of Micah</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/NF3JPQYS</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/NF3JPQYS</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/NF3JPQYS</idno><imprint><date>1995</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">This dissertation examines translation technique in the Peshitta of Micah. The study analyzes and characterizes the Syriac translation of this prophetic book. The model integrates grammatical and lexical data from the book, and then applies the results toward a textual commentary on the Syriac translation. The creation of a database containing all readings of the Syriac, Hebrew and Greek versions allows consideration of all textual data. The introductory chapter describes the methodology and goals of this study. Chapter two establishes the context for this research by summarizing the contribution of recent Peshitta studies and investigating the issues, assumptions, and limitations of previous works. Chapters three and four present an analysis of the Syriac translation of Micah. Lexical and grammatical data are summarized and equivalencies for each linguistic classification are set forth. Analysis includes both forward (Hebrew to Syriac) and reverse (Syriac to Hebrew) data sets. Chapter three presents the results of the grammatical analysis. Chapter four profiles the findings regarding lexical equivalence. Chapter five lays the groundwork for a commentary on the Peshitta of Micah. A clause-by-clause analysis comparing the Syriac translation with the Hebrew and Greek texts reveals the translator's understanding of the source text. The application of the lexical and grammatical findings of chapters three and four demonstrates the bearing that the study of translation technique has on text critical decisions. The main conclusion is that the Syriac of Micah is a combination of both formal and dynamic equivalence. In grammar and syntax the translation is an example of formal-equivalence, whereas lexically and semantically there is a tendency towards dynamic equivalence. The Peshitta version of Micah is in good Syriac style and is not constrained by any theological or exegetical agenda. The Syriac rendering is made independently of the Septuagint and stands very close to the Masoretic tradition.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Magary, Dennis Robert. “Translation Technique in the Peshitta of the Book of Micah.” Ph.D. dissertation, The University of Wisconsin, Madison, 1995.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Translation%20Technique%20in%20the%20Peshitta%20of%20the%20Book%20of%20Micah&amp;amp;rft.inst=The%20University%20of%20Wisconsin%2C%20Madison&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Dennis%20Robert&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Magary&amp;amp;rft.au=Dennis%20Robert%20Magary&amp;amp;rft.date=1995&amp;amp;rft.tpages=513"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Dennis Robert Magary, <title level="a">Translation Technique in the Peshitta of the Book of Micah</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, The University of Wisconsin, Madison, 1995).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/NF3JPQYS" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Micah</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/NF3JPQYS" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Old Testament</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/NF3JPQYS" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Peshitta OT</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/NF3JPQYS" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Prophets</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/NF3JPQYS" ref="dc:subject"><desc>translation</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>