<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">The Christology of Abu Ra’ita at-Takriti: Continuity or Break with Tradition</title><title level="j">Христианство на Ближнем Востоке</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/NR579T7N/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2025-05-20-05:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2025-05-20-05:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><analytic><author><forename>Oleg</forename><surname>Davydenkov</surname></author><title level="a">The Christology of Abu Ra’ita at-Takriti: Continuity or Break with Tradition</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/NR579T7N</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/NR579T7N</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/NR579T7N</idno></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Христианство на Ближнем Востоке</title><textLang mainLang="Russian"/><biblScope unit="vol">8:3</biblScope><imprint><date>2024</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">21-33</biblScope></monogr><note type="abstract">In the first part of this article, an attempt is made to reconstruct the Christological system of the Jacobite theologian Abu Ra’ita at-Takriti (1st half of the 9th century). Abu Ra’ita teaches about one essence of the incarnate God the Word, which is composed of two essences — Divine and human. However, for at-Takriti, the unity of essence does not mean the merging of Divinity and humanity in the sense of the formation of a new property; he recognizes the preservation of the qualitative difference between the components of the composition (“difference in natural quiddity”). Abu Ra’ita’s Christological polemics indicate that he does not make a fundamental distinction between Orthodox Chalcedonian Christology and Nestorianism. In the second part a comparison is made of the Christological systems of Abu Ra’ita and Severus of Antioch, as a result of which it is established that, from the point of view of both Christological problematics and the theological language used, there are very significant differences between the two authors. The final part notes the features of the Christological teaching of Abu Ra’ita. He understands the incarnation not as a unity of two essences, but rather as a kind of “development” of substance (ḏāt) of the Word: the Son of God acquires new, human, essential properties, and the complexity of His essence after incarnation lies in the fact that He has two rows of essential attributes (aṣ-ṣifatān) — Divine and human. Unlike Severus, who resolutely rejected the doctrine of the unity of the essence of Christ, at-Takriti conceives of the complex essence of the incarnate Word in fact as a new species, although represented by only one individual. In this respect, Abu Ra’ita is close to Sergius the Grammarian, one of Severus’ opponents within the Monophysite camp. According to formal criteria, Abu Ra’ita’s Christology should be qualified as a type of moderate monophysitism. However, it is absolutely impossible to consider Abu Ra’ita as a successor of the Severian tradition. His doctrine is an example of a significantly different and, moreover, more radical Monophysite teaching.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Davydenkov, Oleg. “The Christology of Abu Ra’ita at-Takriti: Continuity or Break with Tradition.” <title level="m">Христианство на Ближнем Востоке</title> 8:3 (2024): 21–33. https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.24412/2587-9316-2024-0120.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_id=info%3Adoi%2Fhttps%3A%2F%2Fdoi.org%2F10.24412%2F2587-9316-2024-0120&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Ajournal&amp;amp;rft.genre=article&amp;amp;rft.atitle=The%20Christology%20of%20Abu%20Ra%E2%80%99ita%20at-Takriti%3A%20Continuity%20or%20Break%20with%20Tradition&amp;amp;rft.jtitle=%D0%A5%D1%80%D0%B8%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B8%D0%B0%D0%BD%D1%81%D1%82%D0%B2%D0%BE%20%D0%BD%D0%B0%20%D0%91%D0%BB%D0%B8%D0%B6%D0%BD%D0%B5%D0%BC%20%D0%92%D0%BE%D1%81%D1%82%D0%BE%D0%BA%D0%B5&amp;amp;rft.volume=8%3A3&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Oleg&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Davydenkov&amp;amp;rft.au=Oleg%20Davydenkov&amp;amp;rft.date=2024&amp;amp;rft.pages=21-33&amp;amp;rft.spage=21&amp;amp;rft.epage=33&amp;amp;rft.language=Russian"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Oleg Davydenkov, <title level="a">The Christology of Abu Ra’ita at-Takriti: Continuity or Break with Tradition,</title> <title level="m">Христианство на Ближнем Востоке</title> 8:3 (2024): 21–33, https://doi.org/https://doi.org/10.24412/2587-9316-2024-0120.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>