<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Theodore of Mopsuestia. Commentary on the Gospel of John</title><title level="s">Early Christian Studies 7</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/P8PE4WZH/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>George</forename><surname>Kalantzis</surname></author><title level="m">Theodore of Mopsuestia. Commentary on the Gospel of John</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/P8PE4WZH</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/P8PE4WZH</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/P8PE4WZH</idno><imprint><pubPlace>Strathfield, NSW</pubPlace><publisher>St Pauls Publications</publisher><date>2004</date></imprint></monogr><series><title level="s">Early Christian Studies 7</title></series><note type="abstract">This is the first English translation, with an introduction, a few notes, and brief appendix, of the surviving Greek fragments of Theodore’s Commentary, written probably some time in the first decade of the fifth century. The 140 fragments, drawn from various catenae, were collected after critical evaluation and published in 1948 by Robert Devreesse in an edition which superseded that reproduced in Migne, PG 66. A Syriac version of the Commentary, published in CSCO by Vosté in 1940, shows differences from the Greek. These are imperfectly explained here in the appendix as adaptations of the work to the Syriac Bible text and to East Syrian dualist Christology. It is as probable that Theodore’s characteristic approach was toned down for a catena as enhanced by a translator. The quotations selected for the catenae deal with straightforward questions of the meaning of words, of narrative structure, and the like: with what is necessary to understand the text in the ordinary sense of ‘understand’. Dr Kalantzis has done a useful piece of work. He attends too much to Theodore’s Christology in the introduction and mounts in incongruous and anachronistic terms an apparent defence of its conformity with the standard Patristic model: Theodore is credited with belief in ‘theandric activity’ and ‘hypostatic union’. This is a pity because it misses the point of the quotations preserved in Greek because of Theodore’s perceived value to biblical study, besides sounding so oldfashioned. But, of course, it must be allowed that dismantling catenae in the hope of recovering a lost work was never the best way to understand them or the texts they contain in the first place. [L. R. WICKHAM]</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Kalantzis, George. <title level="m">Theodore of Mopsuestia. Commentary on the Gospel of John</title>. Early Christian Studies 7. Strathfield, NSW: St Pauls Publications, 2004.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Abook&amp;amp;rft.genre=book&amp;amp;rft.btitle=Theodore%20of%20Mopsuestia.%20Commentary%20on%20the%20Gospel%20of%20John&amp;amp;rft.place=Strathfield%2C%20NSW&amp;amp;rft.publisher=St%20Pauls%20Publications&amp;amp;rft.series=Early%20Christian%20Studies%207&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=George&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Kalantzis&amp;amp;rft.au=George%20Kalantzis&amp;amp;rft.date=2004"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">George Kalantzis, <title level="m">Theodore of Mopsuestia. Commentary on the Gospel of John</title>, Early Christian Studies 7 (Strathfield, NSW: St Pauls Publications, 2004).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>