<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">La théologie du salut selon le cycle hebdomadaire syro-antiochien. Étude historique et théologique</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/PMXYHWRT/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Menzer</forename><surname>Habil</surname></author><title level="m">La théologie du salut selon le cycle hebdomadaire syro-antiochien. Étude historique et théologique</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/PMXYHWRT</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/PMXYHWRT</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/PMXYHWRT</idno><imprint><date>2014</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The Syro-Antiochian weekly cycle is an ordinary, simple and non-eucharistic liturgical cycle. The prayer book which we use during the ordinary days, is called Shehimo in Syriac, which means “simple” or “trivial”. The theological value of the services of the Shehimo lies in their actualizing function which transforms the salvational events of the past into a reality that is constantly lived by the faithful through their memory. The study of the book, of its liturgical structure, its content and its sources, reveals the great richness of the weekly cycle which was able to assimilate many biblical, apocryphal, patristic and historical texts in order to present them to the faithful in a simple manner so as to accompany them in their weekly journey from the first to the eighth day of the week. On the other hand, the economy of salvation that was realized by the Word of God constitutes the solid base on which the texts of the Shehimo are founded. When God created man He was motivated by His love; when man fell in sin, God has saved him with the same inconceivable divine love. The incarnation of the Son, His life, His teachings, His miracles, His crucifixion, His death and His resurrection always aimed at the salvation of man. In a poetic, imaginative and melodic way, the Christian believer remembers all this salvational and divine work that Christ has accomplished for his sake, and thus the Christian believer affirms his attachment to this work. He chants the glory of his Savior and expresses passionately his desire to be worthy of eternally chanting to Him His glory in His heavenly kingdom.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Habil, Menzer. “La Théologie Du Salut Selon Le Cycle Hebdomadaire Syro-Antiochien. Étude Historique et Théologique.” Thèse de doctorat en Histoire des religions et Anthropologie religieuse, Université Paris-Sorbonne ‒ Paris IV, 2014.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=La%20th%C3%A9ologie%20du%20salut%20selon%20le%20cycle%20hebdomadaire%20syro-antiochien.%20%C3%89tude%20historique%20et%20th%C3%A9ologique&amp;amp;rft.inst=Universit%C3%A9%20Paris-Sorbonne%20%E2%80%92%20Paris%20IV&amp;amp;rft.degree=Th%C3%A8se%20de%20doctorat%20en%20Histoire%20des%20religions%20et%20Anthropologie%20religieuse&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Menzer&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Habil&amp;amp;rft.au=Menzer%20Habil&amp;amp;rft.date=2014"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Menzer Habil, <title level="a">La Théologie Du Salut Selon Le Cycle Hebdomadaire Syro-Antiochien. Étude Historique et Théologique</title> (Thèse de doctorat en Histoire des religions et Anthropologie religieuse, Université Paris-Sorbonne ‒ Paris IV, 2014).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>