<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The Peshiṭta and Syro-Hexapla Translations of Amos 1:3–2:16</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/PRPM9XZ8/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-06-18-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-06-18-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="thesis"><monogr><author><forename>Petronella S.</forename><surname>Verwijs</surname></author><title level="m">The Peshiṭta and Syro-Hexapla Translations of Amos 1:3–2:16</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/bibl/PRPM9XZ8</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/PRPM9XZ8</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/PRPM9XZ8</idno><imprint><date>2004</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The Peshitta and Syro-Hexapla are two translations of the Old Testament into Syriac. The Peshitta is a translation From the Hebrew, received by a Syriac-speaking Jewish or Christian Community in the 1st or 2nd Century CE. The Syro-Hexapla is a translation from the Greek, made for a Christian community in the 7th Century CE. This dissertation determines specific translation techniques used by the respective translators in Amos 1:3-2:16. An analysis of these translation techniques reveals certain aspects of the communities that receive the translations. While previous scholarship has addressed translation techniques in the Dodekapropheton of the Peshitta (of which the section Amos 1:3-2:16 is a part), this study is the first to address the translation techniques used by the Syro-Hexapla in any part of the Dodekapropheton. Through text criticism the respective &lt;i&gt;Vorlage&lt;/i&gt; of the translations are determined. A detailed evaluation of semantics (grammar and vocabulary) is used to extract the translation techniques employed. Several conclusions are reached through text critical evaluation. The &lt;i&gt;Vorlage&lt;/i&gt; of the Peshitta is identical to the consonantal text as found in the Masoretic Text, while the &lt;i&gt;Vorlage&lt;/i&gt; of the Syro-Hexapla is based on the Old Greek. Semantic analysis shows that a dynamic equivalent translation technique is employed by the Peshitta's translator. This translator focuses on a clear communication of the message to the receptor audience, using the Septuagint or Jewish interpretation traditions when the Hebrew text is unclear or ambivalent. The translator of the Syro-Hexapla uses a formal equivalent translation technique, concentrating on an accurate rendering of the Greek text, not consciously seeking help from other translations or versions. The methodology employed in this dissertation proves effective in expanding and refining the findings of other scholars of the same material in the Peshitta. Applying the identical methodology to a thus far untouched study of the translation technique of the Syro-Hexapla's Dodekapropheton provides an impetus to continued work in this area.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Verwijs, Petronella S. “The Peshiṭta and Syro-Hexapla Translations of Amos 1:3–2:16.” Ph.D. dissertation, The Claremont Graduate University, 2004.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=The%20Peshi%E1%B9%ADta%20and%20Syro-Hexapla%20Translations%20of%20Amos%201%3A3%E2%80%932%3A16&amp;amp;rft.inst=The%20Claremont%20Graduate%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Petronella%20S.&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Verwijs&amp;amp;rft.au=Petronella%20S.%20Verwijs&amp;amp;rft.date=2004&amp;amp;rft.tpages=311"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Petronella S. Verwijs, <title level="a">The Peshiṭta and Syro-Hexapla Translations of Amos 1:3–2:16</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, The Claremont Graduate University, 2004).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/PRPM9XZ8" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Amos</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/PRPM9XZ8" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Old Testament</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/PRPM9XZ8" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Peshitta OT</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/PRPM9XZ8" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Prophets</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/PRPM9XZ8" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Syro-Hexapla</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/bibl/PRPM9XZ8" type="subject" ref="dc:subject"><desc>translation</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>