<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The Place of the Syro-Hexapla in the Textual Tradition of the Septuagint of Deuteronomy</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/PUL82WS4/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Larry James</forename><surname>Perkins</surname></author><title level="m">The Place of the Syro-Hexapla in the Textual Tradition of the Septuagint of Deuteronomy</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/PUL82WS4</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/PUL82WS4</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/PUL82WS4</idno><imprint><date>1980</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">Since S. Rordam's initial effort in 1859-61 to provide a translation analysis of Syh in comparison with his Greek text, no detailed attempt has been made to provide in greater detail this necessary control if Syh is to be used accurately in reconstructing the textual history of the Septuagint. His work is limited in scope and therefore in usefulness and precision. The new materials discovered at Tur 'Abdin for Deuteronomy, as well as the publication of the Gottingen Edition of the Septuagint of Deuternonomy, provided a unique opportunity to initiate such a rigorous analysis of Paul's translation technique, with a view to establishing Syh's place in the textual history of the Septuagint of Deuteronomy. Paul's diverse or particular way(s) of translating Greek particles, conjunctions, prepositions, adverbs, adjectives, pronouns, nouns, verb constructions, and proper names were systematically analyzed. The equivalent Syriac constructions were summarized, giving principles for assessing the Greek text Paul used. The accuracy of Syh in transmitting Origen's text- critical signs, his habit of transposition, and the degree to which Syh of Deuteronomy retains or omits hexaplaric materials were investigated. By comparing Syh with other hexaplaric materials, its place within this textual group was established. The non-Septuagintal materials found in the margins of Syh('T) were catalogued and analyzed. That material which was previously unknown in Greek form was given a tentative Greek retroversion. This investigation reaffirms that Paul was very consistent in his translation, using the same Syriac construction(s) usually to render the same Greek construction(s). This determined consistency results in unusual Syriac on many occasions, but rarely does Paul use a Syriac construction which does not occur elsewhere. What makes him distinctive is his repeated use of otherwise less common Syriac constructions to render common Greek constructions into Syriac. Because of this consistency Syh can be used as a witness for its Greek text with great probability. Sometimes the limitations of Syriac idiom made it impossible for Paul to distinguish several Greek constructions (eg. subjunctives and future indicative). Syh must remain neutral as a textual witness in these cases if textual variation does occur. Paul generally used the Peshitto form of proper names when available, but occasionally he substitutes a divergent form more closely aligned with his Greek text. Syh is without doubt part of the main hexaplaric group (including G 82 376 426) in Deuteronomy. It is second only to G in quality and first in quantity of hexaplaric signs and materials. The hexaplaric signs, however, are less accurately maintained in Syh('T) than in Syh('m) and Syh('b). Paul's translation technique sacrificed Syriac style in order to render the content of the Greek as accurately and literally as possible. Consistency of form was maintained only if the meaning of the Greek could be conveyed without distortion. Paul did not hesitate to diverge from his normal translation equivalent if it meant preserving clarity of meaning.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Perkins, Larry James. “The Place of the Syro-Hexapla in the Textual Tradition of the Septuagint of Deuteronomy.” Ph.D. dissertation, University of Toronto, 1980.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=The%20Place%20of%20the%20Syro-Hexapla%20in%20the%20Textual%20Tradition%20of%20the%20Septuagint%20of%20Deuteronomy&amp;amp;rft.inst=University%20of%20Toronto&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Larry%20James&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Perkins&amp;amp;rft.au=Larry%20James%20Perkins&amp;amp;rft.date=1980&amp;amp;rft.tpages=448"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Larry James Perkins, <title level="a">The Place of the Syro-Hexapla in the Textual Tradition of the Septuagint of Deuteronomy</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, University of Toronto, 1980).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>