<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Nestorius in the &lt;i&gt;Bazaar of Heracleides&lt;/i&gt;: A Christology Compatible with the Third Letter and Anathemas of Cyril of Alexandria</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/Q5JDWEW6/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Anthony Christian</forename><surname>Daly</surname></author><title level="m">Nestorius in the &lt;i&gt;Bazaar of Heracleides&lt;/i&gt;: A Christology Compatible with the Third Letter and Anathemas of Cyril of Alexandria</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/Q5JDWEW6</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/Q5JDWEW6</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/Q5JDWEW6</idno><imprint><date>1983</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">Nestorius, Patriarch of Constantinople, was condemned as a heretic by the Third Ecumenical Council of the Church, A.D.431. He was judged to have viewed Christ as two persons, God the Word dwelling in a mere man, not one person. His major theological opponent was Cyril, Patriarch of Alexandria.
Since the discovery near the turn of the century of the so-called Bazaar of Heracleides, a previously unknown treatise by Nestorius, scholars have increasingly disagreed with the verdict condemning Nestorius. The present study compares the doctrine presented in this work with that advanced by Cyril in his Third Letter to Nestorius with its Twelve Anathemas.
The Christologies advanced in these works are compatible, but they differ in emphasis and in metaphysical approach and terminology. Nestorius posits one physis and one hypostasis each to both the humanity and the divinity of Christ. Cyril sometimes follows this usage, but sometimes he assigns only one physis and one hypostasis to the person of Christ as a whole. On the other hand, he always assigns only one prosopon to Christ. Nestorius counts only one common prosopon of the union in Christ, but he distinguishes this from the two natural prosopa, one for each nature of Christ. Both patriarchs agreed about the Christological accuracy of the title theotokos for Mary, the mother of Christ, and about the whole matter of the communicatio idiomatum, or 'exchange of attributes' between the two natures on the basis of the personal unity of Christ. Finally, certain verbal differences between the two controversialists did not amount to real Christological disagreement.
In Appendix A the controversy between Luise Abramowski and Luigi Scipioni over the authenticity of the first part of the Bazaar is discussed. Scipioni's contention that it was written by Nestorius himself seems to be more reasonable, and it is supported by the present study.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Daly, Anthony Christian. “Nestorius in the <title level="m">Bazaar of Heracleides</title>: A Christology Compatible with the Third Letter and Anathemas of Cyril of Alexandria.” Ph.D. dissertation, The University of California, Los Angeles, 1983.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Nestorius%20in%20the%20%3Ci%3EBazaar%20of%20Heracleides%3C%2Fi%3E%3A%20A%20Christology%20Compatible%20with%20the%20Third%20Letter%20and%20Anathemas%20of%20Cyril%20of%20Alexandria&amp;amp;rft.inst=The%20University%20of%20California%2C%20Los%20Angeles&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Anthony%20Christian&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Daly&amp;amp;rft.au=Anthony%20Christian%20Daly&amp;amp;rft.date=1983&amp;amp;rft.tpages=268"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Anthony Christian Daly, <title level="a">Nestorius in the Bazaar of Heracleides</title>: A Christology Compatible with the Third Letter and Anathemas of Cyril of Alexandria” (Ph.D. dissertation, The University of California, Los Angeles, 1983).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>