<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Assyrian Ethnicity in Education in Chicago</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/RAR3Z9SS/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-15-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-15-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="thesis"><monogr><author><forename>May</forename><surname>Abraham</surname></author><title level="m">Assyrian Ethnicity in Education in Chicago</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/RAR3Z9SS</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/RAR3Z9SS</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/RAR3Z9SS</idno><imprint><date>1984</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">This dissertation is an outgrowth of research concerning ethnicity and education, and curriculum development associated with bilingual education. The activities conducted and behaviors maintained by the Assyrian clubs and their radio programs, Mar Dinkha IV’s  Apostolic Catholic Church, Mar Gewargis’ Sunday School, Rev. Shabaz’ Assyrian Bible School are examples that illustrate this translation process of learning. Background concerning the Assyrian heritage, the Aramaic (Syriac) and the Assyrian language summarizes this investigation within the structure of language formation. Scholars’ interpretations and ordinary laymen’s views are presented concerning commonly held assumptions and certain distortions which have been prevalent. New theories hypothesized by scholars are outlined. A definition of Assyrian people today is given to distinguish between the ancient Assyrian and the contemporary one. An independent study of this Assyrian community can be a starting point toward a more unified native-speaking community with new cultural values attached to various traceable and shifting factors appropriate to life here. The study serves to broach Assyrian groups about basic cooperation needed to foster communication between differing factions using democratic principles. Examination of the Chicago Public Schools’ Assyrian Bilingual Program was an important pillar of the research. Since the Assyrian language has already been decoded for the language transmission process, students in this program should be encouraged to view their language clearly. Broad educational objectives and program goals of a model Sunday School and language school are set forth. This description is evaluated against the standards of existing Sunday Schools and bilingual programs. The entities which conduct events to meet the cultural and educational needs of the Assyrian community are observed and interpreted in the light of certain historical, cultural, or religious traditions. However, controversies regarding Assyrian history, ethnic origin, and language formation must be resolved so that practical applications become worthwhile to the Assyrian community. Since communication is a serious expression of ethnic identity, no Assyrian should be denied the exploration of his language, literature, and heritage. Tolerance and understanding is now required; firm dedication to new educational approaches is called for to organize programs which highlight the Assyrian ethnic experience in Chicago.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Abraham, May. “Assyrian Ethnicity in Education in Chicago.” Ph.D. dissertation, Loyola University of Chicago, 1984.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Assyrian%20Ethnicity%20in%20Education%20in%20Chicago&amp;amp;rft.inst=Loyola%20University%20of%20Chicago&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=May&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Abraham&amp;amp;rft.au=May%20Abraham&amp;amp;rft.date=1984&amp;amp;rft.tpages=208"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">May Abraham, <title level="a">Assyrian Ethnicity in Education in Chicago</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, Loyola University of Chicago, 1984).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/RAR3Z9SS" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Assyrians</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/RAR3Z9SS" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Nestorians</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/RAR3Z9SS" ref="dc:subject"><desc>XIX-XXI CE</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/RAR3Z9SS" ref="dc:subject"><desc>XX CE</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/RAR3Z9SS" ref="dc:subject"><desc>diaspora</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/RAR3Z9SS" ref="dc:subject"><desc>education</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/RAR3Z9SS" ref="dc:subject"><desc>ethnicity</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/RAR3Z9SS" ref="dc:subject"><desc>identity</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>