<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The Influence of the Septuagint on the Peshitta: A Re-Evaluation of Criteria in the Light of Comparative Study of the Version in Genesis and Psalms</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/RW3Q9I5Z/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Jerome Alan</forename><surname>Lund</surname></author><title level="m">The Influence of the Septuagint on the Peshitta: A Re-Evaluation of Criteria in the Light of Comparative Study of the Version in Genesis and Psalms</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/RW3Q9I5Z</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/RW3Q9I5Z</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/RW3Q9I5Z</idno><textLang mainLang="Hebrew"/><imprint><date>1988</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The dissertation treats the problem of the direct influence of the Septuagint (= LXX) on the Peshitta (= P) Old Testament in Genesis and Psalms. In secondary literature, the P Old Testament is often described either as significantly shaped by the LXX or as a daughter version of the LXX. These twentieth century views rest largely on two studies, that of J. Hanel on Genesis and that of A. Vogel on Psalms. While Hanel presents an ad hoc list of evidence, Vogel offers three categories of agreement where he finds direct LXX influence. Neither Hanel nor Vogel attempt to be comprehensive in their citation of evidence, but offer only selected examples. In the model advanced by the translator of the P used the LXX as a help when he was confronted with problems. In the model of Vogel, by contrast, a reviser made use of the LXX to correct the already existing P text. In my dissertation I attempt to define and evaluate the criteria used in alleging that the LXX directly influenced the P version of the Hebrew Bible, either at the translation stage or in a subsequent revision. The following criteria were identified and evaluated: shared exegesis, the use of Greek words in Syriac where the Peshitta had a good Syriac equivalent available, translation technique, doublets, shared variants/non- variants, shared variants and the presence of Grecisms in P. My study seeks to be comprehensive by listing all extra-massoretic agreements between P and LXX. For Genesis and Psalms, I concluded that there is no sound evidence to support the theory that the LXX directly influenced P. This result should cause scholars and students to reappraise P and regard it as an independent source of ancient exegesis, translation technique and textual criticism of the Hebrew Bible.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Lund, Jerome Alan. “The Influence of the Septuagint on the Peshitta: A Re-Evaluation of Criteria in the Light of Comparative Study of the Version in Genesis and Psalms.” Ph.D. dissertation, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, 1988.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=The%20Influence%20of%20the%20Septuagint%20on%20the%20Peshitta%3A%20A%20Re-Evaluation%20of%20Criteria%20in%20the%20Light%20of%20Comparative%20Study%20of%20the%20Version%20in%20Genesis%20and%20Psalms&amp;amp;rft.inst=The%20Hebrew%20University%20of%20Jerusalem&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Jerome%20Alan&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Lund&amp;amp;rft.au=Jerome%20Alan%20Lund&amp;amp;rft.date=1988&amp;amp;rft.tpages=419&amp;amp;rft.language=Hebrew"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Jerome Alan Lund, <title level="a">The Influence of the Septuagint on the Peshitta: A Re-Evaluation of Criteria in the Light of Comparative Study of the Version in Genesis and Psalms</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, 1988).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>