<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">Östliches Christentum in Geschichte und Gegenwart – Perspektiven und Hindernisse der Forschung</title><title level="j">Der Islam</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/S3S7GKHA/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><analytic><author><forename>Michael</forename><surname>Marx</surname></author><author><forename>Johannes</forename><surname>Pahlitzsch</surname></author><author><forename>Dorothea</forename><surname>Weltecke</surname></author><title level="a">Östliches Christentum in Geschichte und Gegenwart – Perspektiven und Hindernisse der Forschung</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/S3S7GKHA</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/S3S7GKHA</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/S3S7GKHA</idno></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Der Islam</title><biblScope unit="vol">88:1</biblScope><imprint><date>2012</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">1-10</biblScope></monogr><note type="abstract">Diversity and hybridity, interaction and exchange: these terms compose the thematic focus of this issue of the journal “Der Islam”: Eastern Christianity in History and the Present: Perspectives and Obstacles. The issue features contributions to a conference held in the year 2008. Evaluating the state of research on Eastern Christianity in Germany, the participants observed that this field of academic enquiry is in danger of becoming extinct in this country. Thus, this collection of articles hopefully serves as a catalyst for jumpstarting debate on Eastern Christianity in the German academic community.
The study of Eastern Christian communities’ cultural identity is at the same time ineluctably intertwined with Qur‘anic Studies and Islamic History - i. e. an Islam in dialogue with, but not mimicking Jewish and Christian traditions of the Hijaz. Diversity in the Islamic-ruled world is a historical reality that has been largely ignored in the study of Islam as well.
This edition of “Der Islam” therefore highlights research that considers the interaction between Muslim and non-Muslim groups, as well as the entangled development of the religious traditions, in order to better understand the socio-religious plurality of Western Asia. Interaction and exchange, however, also include moments of conflict and discrimination. As we close upon the one-year anniversary of the “Arab Spring”, the authors are reminded that it is important to consider the worsening condition of Eastern Christian communities today and their representation in Western studies as well as in the political systems they live in.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Marx, Michael, Johannes Pahlitzsch, and Dorothea Weltecke. “Östliches Christentum in Geschichte Und Gegenwart – Perspektiven Und Hindernisse Der Forschung.” <title level="m">Der Islam</title> 88:1 (2012): 1–10.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Ajournal&amp;amp;rft.genre=article&amp;amp;rft.atitle=%C3%96stliches%20Christentum%20in%20Geschichte%20und%20Gegenwart%20%E2%80%93%20Perspektiven%20und%20Hindernisse%20der%20Forschung&amp;amp;rft.jtitle=Der%20Islam&amp;amp;rft.volume=88%3A1&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Michael&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Marx&amp;amp;rft.au=Michael%20Marx&amp;amp;rft.au=Johannes%20Pahlitzsch&amp;amp;rft.au=Dorothea%20Weltecke&amp;amp;rft.date=2012&amp;amp;rft.pages=1-10&amp;amp;rft.spage=1&amp;amp;rft.epage=10"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Michael Marx, Johannes Pahlitzsch, and Dorothea Weltecke, <title level="a">Östliches Christentum in Geschichte Und Gegenwart – Perspektiven Und Hindernisse Der Forschung,</title> <title level="m">Der Islam</title> 88:1 (2012): 1–10.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>