<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">La polemica antimanichea nel VI secolo alla luce delle principali fonti di lingua greca: tradizione, interpretazione, innovazione</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbssS4KNJ68N/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2025-05-16-05:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2025-05-16-05:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Guillermo</forename><surname>Menéndez Sánchez</surname></author><title level="m">La polemica antimanichea nel VI secolo alla luce delle principali fonti di lingua greca: tradizione, interpretazione, innovazione</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbssS4KNJ68N</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/S4KNJ68N</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/S4KNJ68N</idno><imprint><date>2022</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">Despite the numerous studies on the Manichaean religion in the Eastern Mediterranean area, there is not yet a comprehensive research or analysis on the main anti-Manichaean works preserved in Greek language from the 6th century, when the religion suffered the last great persecution under Emperor Justinian. This gap in historiography is even more surprising if we consider the important corpus of studies existing on Manichaeism in other centuries, as well as on other religions and so-called Christian heresies during the same period. For all these reasons, my project intends to offer an analysis of the main anti-Manichaean sources from the 6th century preserved in Greek: The Abjuration Formula Capita VII contra Manichaeos, the Disputatio of Paul the Persian against the Manichaean Photeinos, the fictitious Disputatio cum Manichaeo of John the Orthodox, the Homiliae I-II of John the Grammarian, and the account of the Manichaean mythology in Simplicius’ Commentarius in Epicteti Enchiridion. The analysis will be mainly focused on the Manichaean tenets and dogmas conserved in these sources, trying to identify the new knowledge that the Greek literature had of the Religion of Light. In addition, attention will be paid to the influence of other earlier anti-Manichaean works exerted upon these documents to provide evidence about the most characteristic Manichaean dogmas for Greek Christianity. Finally, we wish to develop both a comprehensive compilation and an interrelated analysis of these sources, with the purpose of “filling the gap” in the studies on Greek literature Manichaeism, while offering a useful monograph for further research on Manichaeism in the Eastern Roman Empire during the Late-Antiquity.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Menéndez Sánchez, Guillermo. “La Polemica Antimanichea Nel VI Secolo Alla Luce Delle Principali Fonti Di Lingua Greca: Tradizione, Interpretazione, Innovazione.” Tesi di dottorato in studi storici, geografici, antropologici, Università degli Studi di Padova, 2022.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=La%20polemica%20antimanichea%20nel%20VI%20secolo%20alla%20luce%20delle%20principali%20fonti%20di%20lingua%20greca%3A%20tradizione%2C%20interpretazione%2C%20innovazione&amp;amp;rft.inst=Universit%C3%A0%20degli%20Studi%20di%20Padova&amp;amp;rft.degree=Tesi%20di%20dottorato%20in%20studi%20storici%2C%20geografici%2C%20antropologici&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Guillermo&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Men%C3%A9ndez%20S%C3%A1nchez&amp;amp;rft.au=Guillermo%20Men%C3%A9ndez%20S%C3%A1nchez&amp;amp;rft.date=2022"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Guillermo Menéndez Sánchez, <title level="a">La Polemica Antimanichea Nel VI Secolo Alla Luce Delle Principali Fonti Di Lingua Greca: Tradizione, Interpretazione, Innovazione</title> (Tesi di dottorato in studi storici, geografici, antropologici, Università degli Studi di Padova, 2022).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>