<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">De Mar Babaï le Grand à Mar Denkha IV: la Déclaration christologique commune assyro-catholique de 1994</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/SNIKE52G/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Philippe</forename><surname>Khoshaba</surname></author><title level="m">De Mar Babaï le Grand à Mar Denkha IV: la Déclaration christologique commune assyro-catholique de 1994</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/SNIKE52G</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/SNIKE52G</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/SNIKE52G</idno><imprint><date>2017</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The Common Christological Declaration signed in Rome in 1994 between the Catholic Church and the Assyrian Church testifies to a genuine desire for a return to the common faith between the two Churches. It puts an end to a separation dating from the 5th century, due to the Christological quarrels between the two patriarchs Nestorius and Cyril of Alexandria. The Church of the East has always had a double isolation: one geographical, political and cultural since it was formerly outside the borders of the Roman Empire, and the other dogmatic and ecclesiological due to its defense of ecumenical masters condemned such as Nestorius and Theodore de Mopsueste. It exploits the anthropological terms kyana (nature), qnoma and parsopa (person), of the Syriac language, at the basis of the controversies and misunderstandings on the one person in Christ. In this debate, the role of Mar Baba the Great in the seventh century is crucial, for in his book Liber de Unione he gives a precise definition of these terms and systematizes Syro-Oriental theology. He is at the origin of the Christological confession: two natures, two qnome in one person. The Christological Declaration of 1994 reveals to the world what unites the two Churches: the person of Christ. It is the result of a concerted effort by the Pontifical Council for the Promotion of the Unity of Christians and the Church of the East. The desire of Mar Denkha IV to sign achristological agreement with Rome met that of André de Halleux on the Catholic side and Mar Bawai Soro on the Assyrian side. The Assyro-Catholic Joint Committee continued this task with a view to unity, from 1995 to 2004, supported by the "Pro Oriente" Foundation. In 2005, the dialogue was suspended with the refusal of the Assyrians to sign the agreement on the sacraments. The year 2007, aims at resuming the dialogue between the two parties.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Khoshaba, Philippe. “De Mar Babaï Le Grand à Mar Denkha IV: La Déclaration Christologique Commune Assyro-Catholique de 1994.” Thèse de doctorat en Théologie catholique, École doctorale Théologie et sciences religieuses, Strasbourg, 2017.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=De%20Mar%20Baba%C3%AF%20le%20Grand%20%C3%A0%20Mar%20Denkha%20IV%3A%20la%20D%C3%A9claration%20christologique%20commune%20assyro-catholique%20de%201994&amp;amp;rft.inst=%C3%89cole%20doctorale%20Th%C3%A9ologie%20et%20sciences%20religieuses%2C%20Strasbourg&amp;amp;rft.degree=Th%C3%A8se%20de%20doctorat%20en%20Th%C3%A9ologie%20catholique&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Philippe&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Khoshaba&amp;amp;rft.au=Philippe%20Khoshaba&amp;amp;rft.date=2017"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Philippe Khoshaba, <title level="a">De Mar Babaï Le Grand à Mar Denkha IV: La Déclaration Christologique Commune Assyro-Catholique de 1994</title> (Thèse de doctorat en Théologie catholique, École doctorale Théologie et sciences religieuses, Strasbourg, 2017).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>