<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The Syriac Version of Epistle CCII of Gregory Nazianzen</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbssT3QDPDG4/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2025-05-16-05:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2025-05-16-05:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Leonardo</forename><surname>Buscemi</surname></author><title level="m">The Syriac Version of Epistle CCII of Gregory Nazianzen</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbssT3QDPDG4</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/T3QDPDG4</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/T3QDPDG4</idno><imprint><date>2024</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The project presents and edition and translation of the Syriac version of Epistle CCII of Gregory Nazianzen. This Epistle in Syriac has not been previously edited. The edition was done on the basis of two manuscripts, both held at the British Library: BL Add. 14,549, and BL Add. 14,726. There are no lacunae in the edition, since whatever had deteriorated in one manuscript was legible in the other. The English translation of the Syriac makes evident the ways and extent to which the Syriac version differs from the original Greek Epistle. These differences are also discussed extensively in a commentary which compares the Syriac version with its Greek original. Additionally, other manuscripts which contain Syriac translations of the Epistles of Gregory Nazianzen are discussed, wherein a presentation is made of which Epistles exist in one or more copies, and in which manuscripts. This work shows that at least fifty-three of the Epistles of Gregory Nazianzen have been preserved in Syriac, comprising a significant amount of text. Finally, the translational style of Epistle CCII is analyzed in comparison with the various versions of the Orations in Syriac, demonstrating that Epistle CCII is in many ways different stylistically from those Orations which were revised by Paul of Edessa.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Buscemi, Leonardo. “The Syriac Version of Epistle CCII of Gregory Nazianzen.” Master en langues et lettres anciennes, Université catholique de Louvain, 2024.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=The%20Syriac%20Version%20of%20Epistle%20CCII%20of%20Gregory%20Nazianzen&amp;amp;rft.inst=Universit%C3%A9%20catholique%20de%20Louvain&amp;amp;rft.degree=Master%20en%20langues%20et%20lettres%20anciennes&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Leonardo&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Buscemi&amp;amp;rft.au=Leonardo%20Buscemi&amp;amp;rft.date=2024"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Leonardo Buscemi, <title level="a">The Syriac Version of Epistle CCII of Gregory Nazianzen</title> (Master en langues et lettres anciennes, Université catholique de Louvain, 2024).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>