<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Divine Law, Asceticism, and Gender in Aphrahat’s ‘Demonstrations’, with a Complete Annotated Translation of the Text and Comprehensive Syriac Glossary</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/T8X944II/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Adam Isaac</forename><surname>Lehto</surname></author><title level="m">Divine Law, Asceticism, and Gender in Aphrahat’s ‘Demonstrations’, with a Complete Annotated Translation of the Text and Comprehensive Syriac Glossary</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/T8X944II</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/T8X944II</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/T8X944II</idno><imprint><date>2003</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">Asceticism, anti-Jewish polemic, and an extensive use of Old Testament are three prominent feature of the Demonstrations of Aphrahat that can be brought together by an examination of the author's concept of divine Law. While many scholars have studied these areas in isolation, the centrality of Law-observance for Aphrahat has been largely overlooked. This emphasis on the Law affirms the basic continuity between the moral commandments of the Old Testament and the New, while adding a new dimension in the ascetic commands of Christ. In contrast to his clear rejection of O.T. ritual law, Aphrahat's high view of the Decalogue and other O.T. moral laws form an important part of his Christian spirituality. Christ's call to a higher ascetic way of life does not conflict with a fundamental commitment to the moral code already known to the Jewish patriarchs. Though his role clearly goes beyond this, Christ for Aphrahat functions as a new and final teacher of the Law who points to love as the fulfillment of the Law. This emphasis on love, however, is a way of appreciating the fullness of the Law rather than a way of minimizing its importance. In its ethical aspect, Aphrahat's concept of divine Law highlights continuity rather than discontinuity between Judaism and Christianity. This study also provides a gender perspective on Law which reveals that the author, despite some harsh descriptions of women, is perhaps more egalitarian than it first seems. This can be affirmed while recognizing the male bias of the text. To facilitate the present study, and as a contribution to the field in its own right, a full and original translation of the text is provided, along with a comprehensive Syriac glossary which includes virtually all of the terms in the text of the Demonstrations.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Lehto, Adam Isaac. “Divine Law, Asceticism, and Gender in Aphrahat’s ‘Demonstrations’, with a Complete Annotated Translation of the Text and Comprehensive Syriac Glossary.” Ph.D. dissertation, University of Toronto, 2003.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Divine%20Law%2C%20Asceticism%2C%20and%20Gender%20in%20Aphrahat%E2%80%99s%20%E2%80%98Demonstrations%E2%80%99%2C%20with%20a%20Complete%20Annotated%20Translation%20of%20the%20Text%20and%20Comprehensive%20Syriac%20Glossary&amp;amp;rft.inst=University%20of%20Toronto&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Adam%20Isaac&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Lehto&amp;amp;rft.au=Adam%20Isaac%20Lehto&amp;amp;rft.date=2003&amp;amp;rft.tpages=569"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Adam Isaac Lehto, <title level="a">Divine Law, Asceticism, and Gender in Aphrahat’s ‘Demonstrations’, with a Complete Annotated Translation of the Text and Comprehensive Syriac Glossary</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, University of Toronto, 2003).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>