<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Les Chroniques de Mossoul 1855–1920</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbssTCJSSML5/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2025-05-16-05:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2025-05-16-05:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Omar</forename><surname>Mohammed</surname></author><title level="m">Les Chroniques de Mossoul 1855–1920</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbssTCJSSML5</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/TCJSSML5</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/TCJSSML5</idno><imprint><date>2023</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">This dissertation primarily revolves around the historical trajectory of Mosul from 1855 to 1920, with a specific focus on the works of Behnam Badriyya. His seminal document, Tawarikh Al Mawsil, serves as the primary source and central subject of investigation in this study. Chapter I is titled 'Life and Works of Behnam Badriyya'. This chapter presents an in-depth biography of Behnam Badriyya, outlining his life and providing crucial context for understanding his contributions. Furthermore, this chapter delves into the methodological aspects of Badriyya's work by examining his historiography, thoroughly investigating the primary sources of his knowledge and his approach to writing history. This chapter pays special attention to Badriyya's intellectual contributions in diverse fields such as linguistics, history, editing, and translation. The chapter thus forms a solid foundation for understanding Badriyya's work and its influence on our study of Mosul's history. Chapter II, titled 'Tawarikh Al Mawsil', turns the spotlight on Badriyya's seminal work. It commences by setting the stage for understanding the larger context of Mosul's historiography during the 19th century. Following this introduction, the chapter moves towards a chronological assessment of Badriyya's works, validating his authorship and evaluating his methodology. The chapter subsequently takes a deep dive into the nuances of 'Tawarikh Al Mawsil', specifically examining the manuscript, scrutinizing its content, style, and overall historical significance. In Chapter III, the focus shifts to the 'Urban Space of Mosul'. This chapter provides an in-depth exploration of Mosul's urban landscape during the era covered in this dissertation. It examines the city's interreligious dynamics, investigating how different religious communities coexisted and interacted within the city's confines. The chapter further analyzes the city's social dynamics, highlighting the relationships and interactions among different social groups. Political dynamics and social relations are also explored, providing a comprehensive picture of the political landscape of Mosul during this time. The chapter concludes with a discussion on the city's economic dynamics, offering insight into the various forces that shaped the city's economic trajectory. The concluding chapter, Chapter IV, titled 'Mosul Before WWI', looks into the conditions of Mosul during the crucial period leading up to World War I. It offers a detailed review of the social, political, and economic circumstances of the city, elucidating how these factors intertwined and influenced the course of Mosul's history. The second volume of this dissertation presents the English translation of Badriyya's two primary historical compositions, 'Tawarikh al Mawsil' and 'Nubadh fi Tarikh al Ghalaa.' This translation endeavor aims to augment academic discourse by making these significant texts accessible to scholars worldwide.In addition, the second volume includes the original Arabic manuscripts from Badriyya's diverse corpus of work and a vintage photograph of him dating back to 1895. These elements serve to offer readers a more comprehensive and tangible connection to the author and his historical context.This dissertation presents a vivid tapestry of Mosul's history from 1855 to 1920. Using the works of Behnam Badriyya as a central point of reference, it weaves together a multifaceted understanding of the city's past, providing valuable insights for future studies on this historical period.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Mohammed, Omar. “Les Chroniques de Mossoul 1855–1920.” Thèse de doctorat en Histoire et civilisations, École des hautes études en sciences sociales, 2023.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Les%20Chroniques%20de%20Mossoul%201855%E2%80%931920&amp;amp;rft.inst=%C3%89cole%20des%20hautes%20%C3%A9tudes%20en%20sciences%20sociales&amp;amp;rft.degree=Th%C3%A8se%20de%20doctorat%20en%20Histoire%20et%20civilisations&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Omar&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Mohammed&amp;amp;rft.au=Omar%20Mohammed&amp;amp;rft.date=2023"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Omar Mohammed, <title level="a">Les Chroniques de Mossoul 1855–1920</title> (Thèse de doctorat en Histoire et civilisations, École des hautes études en sciences sociales, 2023).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>