<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The Fields, Flocks, and Finances of Monks: Economic Life at Nestorian Monasteries, 500-850</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/TV5UVMXV/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Cynthia Jan</forename><surname>Villagomez</surname></author><title level="m">The Fields, Flocks, and Finances of Monks: Economic Life at Nestorian Monasteries, 500-850</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/TV5UVMXV</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/TV5UVMXV</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/TV5UVMXV</idno><imprint><date>1998</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">Nestorian Monasteries of the East Syrian Orient are considered to be important economic institutions in late Sasanian and early Islamic times. Syriac and Arabic sources, including church and monastic histories, saints' lives, liturgies, synod rulings, and the letters of Church officials are used to describe economic life at Nestorian monasteries. These institutions are shown to provide examples of Nestorian commercial enterprise and communal ownership. It is demonstrated that Nestorian monasteries were actively involved in the production, exchange, and appropriation of wealth in the forms of cash, land, flocks, and precious objects, and occupied a central position within urban and rural economic networks. It is argued that Nestorian monasticism was pervaded by attitudes which called for the renunciation of personal wealth and luxurious living. However, these views did not negate the importance of communal economic assets and activities, but were balanced by the  recognition of the need for monasteries to secure adequate economic resources for sustenance, and provision of charity to the needy. Beth 'Abhe is given special attention as a wealthy, powerful monastery in Sasanian and Islamic Iraq. Drawing upon information from The Book of Governors, written by Thomas of Marga in 840, Beth 'Abhe's economic prosperity is explained as a consequence of its relations with rich Persian Christian patrons, and effective economic management.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Villagomez, Cynthia Jan. “The Fields, Flocks, and Finances of Monks: Economic Life at Nestorian Monasteries, 500-850.” Ph.D. dissertation, University of California, Los Angeles, 1998.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=The%20Fields%2C%20Flocks%2C%20and%20Finances%20of%20Monks%3A%20Economic%20Life%20at%20Nestorian%20Monasteries%2C%20500-850&amp;amp;rft.inst=University%20of%20California%2C%20Los%20Angeles&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Cynthia%20Jan&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Villagomez&amp;amp;rft.au=Cynthia%20Jan%20Villagomez&amp;amp;rft.date=1998&amp;amp;rft.tpages=215"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Cynthia Jan Villagomez, <title level="a">The Fields, Flocks, and Finances of Monks: Economic Life at Nestorian Monasteries, 500-850</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, University of California, Los Angeles, 1998).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>