<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Prepositional Usage in the Old Syriac Gospels</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/V4P8E59S/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Ronald Charles</forename><surname>Owens</surname></author><title level="m">Prepositional Usage in the Old Syriac Gospels</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/V4P8E59S</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/V4P8E59S</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/V4P8E59S</idno><imprint><date>1984</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">This is a synchronic analysis of Syriac prepositions in the Sinai manuscripts of the Gospels, which seeks to explain attested usages and develop theoretical understandings of how they function. The analysis posits that each use of a preposition can be related back to a single Gesamtbedeutung. To ascertain Gesamtbedeutungen, I accord primacy to verbless uses of prepositions (as sole clause predicators, especially locatives). I then analyze (sometimes with aid from a theory of grammatical localism) verb clause usage. The most basic prepositions are:  l- COINCIDE ('at'); b- COINCIDE INTERIOR('in'); 'l COINCIDE SURFACE ('in'); lwt PROXIMITY ('by'); 'm ASSOCIATION ('with'). Diachronically complex mn is PARTITIVE, LOCATIVE ('of'), and SEPARATIVE ('from'). Most of the prepositions are basically locative, but combined with verbs of motion, they result syntagmically in l- TO COINCIDE ('to'), etc. Usage in the corpus is largely unproblematic. Overlapping usages do occur and occasional free interchanges of prepositions can be cited, but to no greater degree than one might expect to find in any language. Overlap is generally of two kinds. One is related to the specifying functions of prepositions. For example, l-, b-, 'l, lwt, and syd each occur with the existential particle 'yt to form possessive expressions. But while l-, in its vagueness, may replace any of the other prepositions in such expressions, locative specificity is sacrificed. Moreover, in these constructions b-, 'l and lwt are not mutually interchangeable. Their selection is restriced by the entities predicated. The second kind of overlap occurs when certain derived functions of different prepositions merge. For example, l-, b-, and mn each mark agent functions, but not interchangeably. L- agents are restricted to a single type of syntagm; b- agents are normally mediate (or instrumental); mn agents are immediate, usually occurring only with passive verbs. This investigation was prompted by allegations that Semitic prepositions are often ambiguous and freely interchangeable. My conclusion is that in Syriac the claim is unsupported by the evidence. Most ambiguity is more properly termed vagueness, and most presumed interchangeability proves to be mere appearance.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Owens, Ronald Charles. “Prepositional Usage in the Old Syriac Gospels.” Ph.D. dissertation, Brandeis University, 1984.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Prepositional%20Usage%20in%20the%20Old%20Syriac%20Gospels&amp;amp;rft.inst=Brandeis%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Ronald%20Charles&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Owens&amp;amp;rft.au=Ronald%20Charles%20Owens&amp;amp;rft.date=1984&amp;amp;rft.tpages=545"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Ronald Charles Owens, <title level="a">Prepositional Usage in the Old Syriac Gospels</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, Brandeis University, 1984).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>