<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Εὐωδία: The Use and Meaning of Fragrances in the Ancient World and Their Christianization (100-900 AD)</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/VIHHG25I/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Béatrice</forename><surname>Caseau</surname></author><title level="m">Εὐωδία: The Use and Meaning of Fragrances in the Ancient World and Their Christianization (100-900 AD)</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/VIHHG25I</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/VIHHG25I</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/VIHHG25I</idno><imprint><date>1994</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">In this dissertation, I study the meanings of odors in the Ancient and early Medieval world and I propose a solution to the question of the introduction of incense in the Christian churches. I also reflect on the meaning of the perfume added to the myron or holy chrism. I assumed that, in order to understand the symbolic significance of odors, it was essential to give full attention to the different moments and places where odors, especially sweet-smelling scents were present, tracking archaeological data and economical facts.
Chapter one is devoted to understand the religious use of incense in the concurrent religions and the repulsion Christians developed towards idolatrous incense. Chapter two explains why it was very difficult for Christian Apologists to speak against incense, since it belonged to the world of fragrances and, as such, was used to create safe, pleasurable spaces as well as to honor the living and the dead. Because the Christians adopted regional burial practices, they often used incense and other perfumes for the care of their dead. Chapter three explains the fear that stench, and particularly the odor of death, inspired to all. This is why the practice of embalming the dead, even if only externally, was widespread. The properties of fragrant spices to restrain the process of putrefaction were well known. Those same qualities were used in medicine to heal wounds. Also, since danger was thought to come from stench, incense was commended for its capacity to protect those who inhaled it. Chapter four studies how this medical knowledge came to be part of Christian rhetoric and practices. Chapter five is devoted to the use of incense and other perfumes in Late Antique and early Byzantine churches.
The process of christianization of aromatic substances, as well as the role these substances played in the life of men and women of the Ancient and early Medieval periods, are the central themes of this dissertation.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Caseau, Béatrice. “Εὐωδία: The Use and Meaning of Fragrances in the Ancient World and Their Christianization (100-900 AD).” Ph.D. dissertation, Princeton University, 1994.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=%CE%95%E1%BD%90%CF%89%CE%B4%CE%AF%CE%B1%3A%20The%20Use%20and%20Meaning%20of%20Fragrances%20in%20the%20Ancient%20World%20and%20Their%20Christianization%20(100-900%20AD)&amp;amp;rft.inst=Princeton%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=B%C3%A9atrice&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Caseau&amp;amp;rft.au=B%C3%A9atrice%20Caseau&amp;amp;rft.date=1994"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Béatrice Caseau, <title level="a">Εὐωδία: The Use and Meaning of Fragrances in the Ancient World and Their Christianization (100-900 AD)</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, Princeton University, 1994).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>