<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">O Livro siríaco de Daniel: texto, tradução e comentário</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/W7XI995J/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-09-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-09-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Marcus Vinícius</forename><surname>Ramos</surname></author><title level="m">O Livro siríaco de Daniel: texto, tradução e comentário</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/W7XI995J</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/W7XI995J</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/W7XI995J</idno><imprint><date>2014</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">Traditionally considered a “literature of resistance”, the apocalypses have been treated over the past decades as a purely literary genre. Under this understanding, those studying these texts foregrounded textual and exegetical issues, isolated the modes of thought, and identified their social contexts. This framework does not always suit, however, many apocalypses written in the early centuries of the Common Era, especially those assigned to Daniel. Composed in various languages and mostly without signs of mutual dependence, many of these texts are supported by different traditions, such as the coming of Antichrist or the “revolt of the peoples of the north” at the end of times, led by Gog and Magog. The Syriac Apocalypse of Daniel, virtually unknown until early this century, seems to be one of them: its text is used in this thesis as a research tool for better understanding the history of the Syriac Christianity in the seventh century. The following issues are considered here: (1) The reception of the Book of Daniel in the early church; (2) The origins and associations of Gog, Magog and Antichrist; (3) The original text of the Syriac Apocalypse of Daniel and its translation into Portuguese; and (4) A critical commentary on the Syriac Apocalypse of Daniel. The findings indicate that the Syriac Apocalypse of Daniel, focused on the imminent end of history, did not provide the necessary hope, defined in political terms, for the survival of the Byzantine Empire.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Ramos, Marcus Vinícius. “O Livro Siríaco de Daniel: Texto, Tradução e Comentário.” Tese de doutorado em História, Universidade de Brasília, 2014.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=O%20Livro%20sir%C3%ADaco%20de%20Daniel%3A%20texto%2C%20tradu%C3%A7%C3%A3o%20e%20coment%C3%A1rio&amp;amp;rft.inst=Universidade%20de%20Bras%C3%ADlia&amp;amp;rft.degree=Tese%20de%20doutorado%20em%20Hist%C3%B3ria&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Marcus%20Vin%C3%ADcius&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Ramos&amp;amp;rft.au=Marcus%20Vin%C3%ADcius%20Ramos&amp;amp;rft.date=2014"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Marcus Vinícius Ramos, <title level="a">O Livro Siríaco de Daniel: Texto, Tradução e Comentário</title> (Tese de doutorado em História, Universidade de Brasília, 2014).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>