<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">The Syriac Apocryphal Psalms: Text, Texture, and Commentary</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/WEFZN4UW/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-15-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-15-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="thesis"><monogr><author><forename>Stanley Calvin</forename><surname>Pigué</surname></author><title level="m">The Syriac Apocryphal Psalms: Text, Texture, and Commentary</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/WEFZN4UW</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/WEFZN4UW</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/WEFZN4UW</idno><imprint><date>1988</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">The purpose of this dissertation was to explore the collective significance of the five Syriac Apocryphal Psalms. Although work has been done on each of the psalms individually, a need exists for further study on the collective importance of these works. Chapter 2 presented the texts and translations of these psalms along with discussion on textual problems and variant readings. Hebrew, Greek and Syriac texts were analyzed and compared. Chapter 3 approached the texture of these psalms. The literary structure, the form, and the Vorlage were discussed. Psalm 151 and 152 are chiastic structures. Psalm 153 is an inverted chiasmus. Psalm 154 exhibits elements of a conflation of two shorter psalms. However, the literary evidence argues for a single composition or for the pre-existence of one psalm around which a second psalm was composed. Psalm 155 is an alphabetic acrostic from aleph to pe. The psalms give evidence of characteristics unique to Late Jewish psalmody. Chapter 4 presented discussions regarding the meaning, source, dating, superscriptions, and functions of the psalms. Psalm 151 is the oldest of the psalms and expresses orthodox biblical theology in a unique style. Psalms 152 and 153 were comprised in a style and structure similar to Psalm 151, and probably date to the early Syriac church. Psalm 154 exhibits strong Wisdom elements, and has phrases and concepts similar to those of the Qumran literature. It was not composed at Qumran, but may be proto-Essenian. Psalm 155 is generic in style and theme and is a product of late Jewish psalmody. Chapter 5 concluded with the impact these psalms have had on the discussion of canon and late Jewish psalmody. Final conclusions were drawn and areas for further study were delineated.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Pigué, Stanley Calvin. “The Syriac Apocryphal Psalms: Text, Texture, and Commentary.” Ph.D. dissertation, The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1988.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=The%20Syriac%20Apocryphal%20Psalms%3A%20Text%2C%20Texture%2C%20and%20Commentary&amp;amp;rft.inst=The%20Southern%20Baptist%20Theological%20Seminary&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Stanley%20Calvin&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Pigu%C3%A9&amp;amp;rft.au=Stanley%20Calvin%20Pigu%C3%A9&amp;amp;rft.date=1988&amp;amp;rft.tpages=253"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Stanley Calvin Pigué, <title level="a">The Syriac Apocryphal Psalms: Text, Texture, and Commentary</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary, 1988).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/WEFZN4UW" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Apocryphal Psalms</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/WEFZN4UW" ref="dc:subject"><desc>OT apocrypha</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/WEFZN4UW" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Qumran</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/WEFZN4UW" ref="dc:subject"><desc>primary sources [Syriac] + English translation</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>