<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">Entering the Holy Place in Syriac Orthodox Liturgy: A Ritual and Theological Analysis</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/WL48CF2P/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Gabriel</forename><surname>Bar-Sawme</surname></author><title level="m">Entering the Holy Place in Syriac Orthodox Liturgy: A Ritual and Theological Analysis</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/WL48CF2P</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/WL48CF2P</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/WL48CF2P</idno><imprint><date>2021</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">Questions concerning sacred spaces and their relationship to ritual is of interest to historians of religion and others as well. How sacred spaces emerge and are constructed and what relationship they have to rituals are some of the areas that are dealt with in this study in relation to Syriac Orthodox liturgy.
The purpose of this study is to create a better understanding of how the Sedrō of Entrance has been practiced in earlier periods and architectural contexts and to investigate what role the entrance rite may have had in constructing the sanctuary as sacred space and the worshipping community as church. 
The Sedrō of Entrance is a prayer employed during the rite of entrance into the altar in Syriac Orthodox Eucharistic liturgy. This study uses ritual theory to frame the rite of entrance and studies the intersection of ritual text, action and place. Two research questions are addressed: a) How is the rite of entrance into the altar, in the Syriac Orthodox liturgy, performed during the 9th-13th centuries? b) How does the rite of entrance construct the sanctuary as sacred space and the worshipping community as church?
The study builds on historical material, manuscripts from the 9th to the 13th centuries, architecture, and other historical textual material. The rite of entrance is framed with ritual theory. Theological analysis is also used to support the ritual theory. The themes of the dissertation include, among others, the relationship between ritual process, ritual place, and the ritual body. It also explores the role of language in the ritual process.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Bar-Sawme, Gabriel. “Entering the Holy Place in Syriac Orthodox Liturgy: A Ritual and Theological Analysis.” Th.D. dissertation, Department of Theology, Uppsala University, 2021.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=Entering%20the%20Holy%20Place%20in%20Syriac%20Orthodox%20Liturgy%3A%20A%20Ritual%20and%20Theological%20Analysis&amp;amp;rft.inst=Department%20of%20Theology%2C%20Uppsala%20University&amp;amp;rft.degree=Th.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Gabriel&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Bar-Sawme&amp;amp;rft.au=Gabriel%20Bar-Sawme&amp;amp;rft.date=2021"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Gabriel Bar-Sawme, <title level="a">Entering the Holy Place in Syriac Orthodox Liturgy: A Ritual and Theological Analysis</title> (Th.D. dissertation, Department of Theology, Uppsala University, 2021).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>