<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">To Imitate Their Perfection: A Comparison of the Relationship of Christology and Martyrial Liturgy in Sixth Century Gaul and Syria</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/WS85WEKZ/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-15-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-15-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct type="thesis"><monogr><author><forename>Lizette Marlene</forename><surname>Larson-Miller</surname></author><title level="m">To Imitate Their Perfection: A Comparison of the Relationship of Christology and Martyrial Liturgy in Sixth Century Gaul and Syria</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/WS85WEKZ</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/WS85WEKZ</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/WS85WEKZ</idno><imprint><date>1992</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">This dissertation continues the discussion, begun in this century, on the significance of the cult of martyrs in the early church and proposes, in addition, that the celebration and theology of the cult of the martyrs is itself influenced by christological concerns in the sixth century, concerns which produced critical differences between East and West with regard to general liturgical practice and the architectural setting of the liturgy.
In order to develop the web of relations between Christ, martyr and Christian which underlie the liturgical and architectural developments of the sixth century, this study begins with an overview of christian death cults and the cult of martyrs in the first four centuries of the church.
The dissertation then turns to an analysis of christological belief in two specific areas of East and West, Syria and Gaul. The christology of Gaul, represented in part by the writings of Gregory of Tours, falls in line with the christology expounded by Leo and the council of Chalcedon but was concerned especially to counter the Western Arianism espoused by the Visigothic Christians. Antioch and much of Syria find a spokesperson in Severus of Antioch, a bishop who defined his position over and against the diphysite Chalcedonian and Nestorian adherents.
The relationship of Christ and martyr was manifested in the role which the martyrs themselves played in Christian society and ritualized in the liturgies surrounding the cult of martyrs. Because of this relationship, the dissertation explores the liturgical expression of these beliefs by investigating both text and architectural setting. This analysis reveals, in Syria, the centrality of Christ in the liturgy, the inviolability of the eucharistic space, and the intimate relationship between Christ and Christian. Conversely, the importance of the martyr as intermediary and primary model, the fusion of eucharist and relic in a single unified architectural focus, and the anti-Arian resistance to seeing Christ as a model for ordinary Christians reflects the theological unrest of sixth century Gaul.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Larson-Miller, Lizette Marlene. “To Imitate Their Perfection: A Comparison of the Relationship of Christology and Martyrial Liturgy in Sixth Century Gaul and Syria.” Ph.D. dissertation, Graduate Theological Union, 1992.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=To%20Imitate%20Their%20Perfection%3A%20A%20Comparison%20of%20the%20Relationship%20of%20Christology%20and%20Martyrial%20Liturgy%20in%20Sixth%20Century%20Gaul%20and%20Syria&amp;amp;rft.inst=Graduate%20Theological%20Union&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Lizette%20Marlene&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Larson-Miller&amp;amp;rft.au=Lizette%20Marlene%20Larson-Miller&amp;amp;rft.date=1992&amp;amp;rft.tpages=372"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Lizette Marlene Larson-Miller, <title level="a">To Imitate Their Perfection: A Comparison of the Relationship of Christology and Martyrial Liturgy in Sixth Century Gaul and Syria</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, Graduate Theological Union, 1992).</bibl><listRelation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/WS85WEKZ" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Christology</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/WS85WEKZ" ref="dc:subject"><desc>Severus of Antioch</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/WS85WEKZ" ref="dc:subject"><desc>VI CE</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/WS85WEKZ" ref="dc:subject"><desc>liturgics</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/WS85WEKZ" ref="dc:subject"><desc>martyrdom</desc></relation><relation active="http://syriaca.org/cbss/WS85WEKZ" ref="dc:subject"><desc>saints</desc></relation></listRelation></body></text></TEI>