<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">On the Armenian Dictionary, Gospel and Inscription Written in Syriac Letters</title><title level="j">Etchmiadzin</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/WVE8BG8X/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><analytic><author><forename>Ruzan</forename><surname>Poghosyan</surname></author><title level="a">On the Armenian Dictionary, Gospel and Inscription Written in Syriac Letters</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/WVE8BG8X</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/WVE8BG8X</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/WVE8BG8X</idno></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Etchmiadzin</title><textLang mainLang="Armenian"/><biblScope unit="vol">5</biblScope><imprint><date>2016</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">64-72</biblScope></monogr><note type="abstract">The Glossary by the Arab author Bar Bahlul of the 10th century, the Gospel of Tigranakert and the copy of the inscription of the church Mardin prove the existence of Syro-Armenian script. D. Margoliute had devoted an article to the Glossary in 1898 which aroused great interest among armenologists. H. Tashian examining the questions connected with the manuscript writing mainly focused on the issue of transliteration. Nevertheless the question of the Armenian dialect, in which the manuscript is written, has not definite answer in D. Margoliut’s and H. Tashyan’s articles. H. Acharyan assumes that it is written in a dialect very close to the one of Tigranakert. We consider that it is the dialect of Edessa, as there are specific grammatical features of this dialect as a definite article with the use of nouns and present tense form in verbal structures. Referring to the inscription, H. Tashian has not accepted that it was written in 450, because the date also in Syriac letters and the stone from which it was copied is missing. The existence of Tigranakert Gospel accidentally became known in 1914, but after a short time it disappeared. It is supposed to be destroyed in 1915-1916 during the massacres of Syrian Christians. D. Margoliut suggests that nothing has been written about the Syro-Armenian manuscripts for many years as they have been kept secret. The data stored about these manuscripts and inscription allow us to say that after the creation of the Armenian alphabet by Mesrop Mashtots the Syro-Armenian script in Armenian Mesopotamia was gradually put out of use and manuscripts, as the Gospel of Tigranakert proves, were kept secret by Syrian priests.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Poghosyan, Ruzan. “On the Armenian Dictionary, Gospel and Inscription Written in Syriac Letters.” <title level="m">Etchmiadzin</title> 5 (2016): 64–72.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Ajournal&amp;amp;rft.genre=article&amp;amp;rft.atitle=On%20the%20Armenian%20Dictionary%2C%20Gospel%20and%20Inscription%20Written%20in%20Syriac%20Letters&amp;amp;rft.jtitle=Etchmiadzin&amp;amp;rft.volume=5&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Ruzan&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Poghosyan&amp;amp;rft.au=Ruzan%20Poghosyan&amp;amp;rft.date=2016&amp;amp;rft.pages=64-72&amp;amp;rft.spage=64&amp;amp;rft.epage=72&amp;amp;rft.language=Armenian"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Ruzan Poghosyan, <title level="a">On the Armenian Dictionary, Gospel and Inscription Written in Syriac Letters,</title> <title level="m">Etchmiadzin</title> 5 (2016): 64–72.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>