<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="a">Logicising Ecclesiastical Conflicts: The Synod of Ḥenanīshō‘ II (775) and the Aristotelian Vogue among East Syrian Scholars</title><title level="j">Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/XM8EN686/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><analytic><author><forename>Vittorio</forename><surname>Berti</surname></author><title level="a">Logicising Ecclesiastical Conflicts: The Synod of Ḥenanīshō‘ II (775) and the Aristotelian Vogue among East Syrian Scholars</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/XM8EN686</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/XM8EN686</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/XM8EN686</idno></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</title><biblScope unit="vol">72:3-4</biblScope><imprint><date>2020</date></imprint><biblScope unit="pp">203-215</biblScope></monogr><note type="abstract">The Synod of Ḥenanīshō‘ II (775 CE) was held at a moment of transition for the Church of the East during the first Abbassid age. The new ruling dynasty had moved the political heart of Islam from Hellenistic Syria into the native space of the Church of the East. The Christians of Iraq for the first time were placed at the centre of an empire that extended from the Mediterranean to the Indian Ocean, from Arabia to Central Asia. In this context, the cultural competences required to administrate and structure such an empire, opened a political space in which East Syrian scholars could gain public legitimacy because of their literary and scientific skills. In this perspective, the strongly hellenizing attitude that Syriac Christian elites cultivated in their monasteries and schools since the 6th century, in particular the study of the Aristotelian logic, became one of the main ways of gaining not only social prestige outside the Church, but also ecclesiastical recognition and hegemony. This cultural dynamics could explain the application of an emphatic logical jargon in the text of the Synod of Ḥenanīshō‘ II. The ecclesiastical assembly electing him was held after a long vacancy of the patriarchal seat of Seleucia-Ctesiphon. Two main factions opposed each other. The text of the synod, handed down to us in the Synodicon Orientale, reflects a complex work of editing documents directed at settling contrasting ecclesiastical groups by a superimposed hermeneutical grid of logical matrix. This contribution aims to explain the meaning and relevance of this logical grid, by clarifying the strategy of the synod and presenting an example of a practical and political application of logical language and reasoning among Syriac speaking elites.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Berti, Vittorio. “Logicising Ecclesiastical Conflicts: The Synod of Ḥenanīshō‘ II (775) and the Aristotelian Vogue among East Syrian Scholars.” <title level="m">Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</title> 72:3-4 (2020): 203–15.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Ajournal&amp;amp;rft.genre=article&amp;amp;rft.atitle=Logicising%20Ecclesiastical%20Conflicts%3A%20The%20Synod%20of%20%E1%B8%A4enan%C4%ABsh%C5%8D%E2%80%98%20II%20(775)%20and%20the%20Aristotelian%20Vogue%20among%20East%20Syrian%20Scholars&amp;amp;rft.jtitle=Journal%20of%20Eastern%20Christian%20Studies&amp;amp;rft.volume=72%3A3-4&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Vittorio&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Berti&amp;amp;rft.au=Vittorio%20Berti&amp;amp;rft.date=2020&amp;amp;rft.pages=203-215&amp;amp;rft.spage=203&amp;amp;rft.epage=215"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Vittorio Berti, <title level="a">Logicising Ecclesiastical Conflicts: The Synod of Ḥenanīshō‘ II (775) and the Aristotelian Vogue among East Syrian Scholars,</title> <title level="m">Journal of Eastern Christian Studies</title> 72:3-4 (2020): 203–15.</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>