<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title level="m">A Heaven of Wine: Muslim-Christian Encounters at Monasteries in the Early Islamic Middle East</title><sponsor>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</sponsor><funder>The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder><funder>The International Balzan Prize Foundation</funder><editor role="general" ref="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#dmichelson">David A. Michelson</editor><editor role="creator" ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</editor><respStmt><resp>Record added to Zotero by</resp><name ref="https://www.zotero.org/cbsc_admin">cbsc_admin</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><authority>Syriaca.org: The Syriac Reference Portal</authority><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/YYB7XMDT/tei</idno><availability>
        <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">
            <p>Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License.</p>
        </licence>
    </availability><date>2024-08-07-04:00</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>Born digital.</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><revisionDesc><change who="http://syriaca.org/documentation/editors.xml#autogenerated" when="2024-08-07-04:00">CREATED: This bibl record was autogenerated from a Zotero record.</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><biblStruct><monogr><author><forename>Elizabeth</forename><surname>Campbell</surname></author><title level="m">A Heaven of Wine: Muslim-Christian Encounters at Monasteries in the Early Islamic Middle East</title><idno type="URI">http://syriaca.org/cbss/YYB7XMDT</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/a_comprehensive_bibliography_on_syriac_studies/items/YYB7XMDT</idno><idno type="URI">https://www.zotero.org/groups/4861694/items/YYB7XMDT</idno><imprint><date>2009</date></imprint></monogr><note type="abstract">This dissertation reconsiders the
                    transition from Christianity to Islam in the Middle East during the
                    half-millenium following the Muslim conquest by investigating the development of
                    Islam in dialogue with Christianity. Monasteries provide an angle for
                    understanding the vital role of Christians, both real and imagined, in the
                    evolution of Muslim identity and the formation of Islamic culture and society.
                    Texts about monasteries participated in a larger Muslim discourse that defined
                    the relationship between Christianity and Islam, the legacy of Christianity in
                    the Muslim community, and Islam itself. They exhibit the process by which
                    Muslims absorbed Christian social and religious spaces and interpreted them in
                    their own tradition.
The works on monasteries of Shabushti (d. ca. 988),
                    Yaqut (d. 1228), and al-`Umari (d. 1349), as well as ascetic biographies,
                    chronicles, and popular romances, show monasteries to be the setting for a wide
                    range of Muslim-Christian interactions. Chapter one describes the Muslim
                    understanding of the physical monastery and its relation to the landscape of the
                    early Islamic Middle East. Chapters two and three examine the Muslim literary
                    tradition about monasteries. In ascetic biographies, the story of the visit to
                    the monastery allowed authors to explore the relation between Muslim and
                    Christian asceticism, either acknowledging shared practices or describing
                    competition between Islam and Christianity. The most prevalent literary trope
                    portrayed monasteries as places to indulge in wine, music, and flirtation. The
                    stories secularized the monastery, turning the sacred Christian space into a
                    place of leisure and indulgence for Muslims. Chapters four and five examine the
                    historical patterns that shaped these texts, the social interaction and cultural
                    dialogue that occurred at monasteries. The stories, although conforming to
                    literary tropes and exaggerated to boast or condemn, originated in actual visits
                    to monasteries, which were the base for Umayyad court ritual, following the
                    practice of their Ghassanid Arab predecessors. Monasteries marked an established
                    network of privileged sites, the backdrop against which a distinctly Muslim
                    sacred topography developed. Finally, post-Crusader legends of Muslim-Christian
                    warfare show that monasteries remained potent symbols of the encounter between
                    Islam and Christianity, sites of both peaceful interaction and violent
                    confrontation.</note></biblStruct><bibl type="formatted" subtype="bibliography" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">
  Campbell, Elizabeth. “A Heaven of Wine: Muslim-Christian Encounters at Monasteries in the Early Islamic Middle East.” Ph.D. dissertation, University of Washington, 2009.
</bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="coins" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition"><ptr target="url_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;ctx_ver=Z39.88-2004&amp;amp;rfr_id=info%3Asid%2Fzotero.org%3A2&amp;amp;rft_val_fmt=info%3Aofi%2Ffmt%3Akev%3Amtx%3Adissertation&amp;amp;rft.title=A%20Heaven%20of%20Wine%3A%20Muslim-Christian%20Encounters%20at%20Monasteries%20in%20the%20Early%20Islamic%20Middle%20East&amp;amp;rft.inst=University%20of%20Washington&amp;amp;rft.degree=Ph.D.%20dissertation&amp;amp;rft.aufirst=Elizabeth&amp;amp;rft.aulast=Campbell&amp;amp;rft.au=Elizabeth%20Campbell&amp;amp;rft.date=2009"/></bibl><bibl type="formatted" subtype="citation" resp="https://www.zotero.org/styles/chicago-note-bibliography-17th-edition">Elizabeth Campbell, <title level="a">A Heaven of Wine: Muslim-Christian Encounters at Monasteries in the Early Islamic Middle East</title> (Ph.D. dissertation, University of Washington, 2009).</bibl><listRelation/></body></text></TEI>